<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Grapes from Canaan, or, The believers present taste of future glory expressed in a short divine poem, the issue of spare hours, and published at the request, and for the entertainment of those whose hopes are above their present enjoyments.</title>
            <author>Taylor, Francis, 1590-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 130 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63574</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T280</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20740</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12563182</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12563182</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63305</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63574)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63305)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 704:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Grapes from Canaan, or, The believers present taste of future glory expressed in a short divine poem, the issue of spare hours, and published at the request, and for the entertainment of those whose hopes are above their present enjoyments.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, Francis, 1590-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32], 87 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.L. for the author ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: prelim. p. [32].</note>
                  <note>Dedicatory signed: Francis Taylor.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63305:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63305:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GRAPES FROM CANAAN; OR THE <hi>Believers</hi> preſent taſte of future Glory: Expreſſed in a ſhort Divine POEM, The iſſue of ſpare Hours: And Publiſhed at the Requeſt, and for the Entertainment of thoſe whoſe hopes are above their preſent enjoyments.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Cor. 13.12.</hi>
                  </bibl> For now we ſee through a glaſs;, darkly; but then face to face: now I know in part, but then ſhall I know, even as alſo I am known.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Joh. 3.2.</hi>
                  </bibl>—Now are we the ſons of God, and it doth not appear yet what we ſhall be; but we know, that when he ſhall appear, we ſhall be like him, for we ſhall ſee him as he is.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. L.</hi> for the Author, and are to be ſold at the ſign of the <hi>Grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:63305:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63305:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable, <hi>Francis Rous</hi> Eſq; Provoſt of <hi>Eaton,</hi> and one of the Council to his Highneſs the Lord <hi>Protector.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honorable Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Hope You will not conceive that I hold any Compliance with the ſcribling humour of this age, or that as dark as I am, I ſhould ſo little ſee into my ſelf, as not to know my rude and undigeſted Labours un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy publick light: When I firſt deſign'd within my ſelf the compoſure of this enſuing <hi>Poem,</hi> my Thoughts were not in the leaſt ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency for a Publication; yet through the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of ſome Friends (whoſe better judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments I could not but value above mine own private Opinion) I have ſont my unfledg'd Muſe abroad into the World, humbly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming
<pb facs="tcp:63305:3"/>the boldneſs to ſhrowd it under the wing of Your Honours Protection, aſſuring my ſelf it will find the better welcom for the name of the Patron. Sir, This ſmall <hi>Manuel,</hi> I confeſs, comes towards you untrimmed, its Innocency being its beſt Dreſs, and its Poetry lying more in Feet than Fancy; yet is it Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox, I hope, and Theologically ſubſtantial: The ſubject matter is Divine, anſwering Your Affections; Sublime, not unbeſeeming Your Perſonage; moſt Neceſſary, and therefore not unworthy Your ſerious Thoughts. And for the Meanneſs of the Author, the Heathen man pleads for me; <hi>Non quis, ſed quid dicit at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendito,</hi> not who ſpeaks, but what is ſpoken ought to be conſidered. This little <hi>Volume,</hi> as it proceeds from me, hath not the leaſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement of a <hi>Tolle, lege,</hi> written upon it, yet (not to diſown the in-comings of Divine aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance) like the ſtone Garamantides, <hi>habet intus Aureas guttas,</hi> it hath Golden Drops within it ſelf, enriching the believing Soul with a lively hope of a bliſsful immortality. My principal inducement of Dedicating this to Your Honor, is, the remembrance of und<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved Favours, which challenge more than
<pb facs="tcp:63305:3"/>an airy Complement at my hands. The ſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Love and Reſpect You bore to my good Father while he lived, and the real Teſtimony of Your continued Affection to my ſelf, hath engaged my moſt active Thoughts to ſtudy ſomething which may in ſome meaſure render me ſenſible of both; Theſe few lines therefore, the firſt Fruits of my weaker Attainments of this Nature, I preſent with all Humility to Your Acceptance, in hope that as they may prove a Mite caſt into the Treaſure of GOD'S glory and the publick good, ſo they will ſignifie to Your Honour a Mind ſenſible of, and a Heart thankeful for the many free and noble Favours vouchſafed to my Relations and my Self. Sir, I am very confident Your judicious Eye may running read many rude unpoliſh't Lines in this Draught of Eternity; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I make it my humble Requeſt, That as the Painter of old drew <hi>Alexander</hi> with his finger upon his defective Eye; So Your known Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour would put a favourable gloſs upon my im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections, and daſh out my <hi>Errata</hi> by a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable connivence. In the confidence whereof I ſhall only raiſe the Application of my humble Suite to Almighty God, That he would make
<pb facs="tcp:63305:4"/>You no leſs faithful in, than able for his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, that after You have had a glimpſe of his glory in the Kingdom of Grace. You may have a fulneſs of his grace in the Kingdom of Glory; with the which Thoughts upon my Heart in the beſt ſeaſons of my Soul, I ſhall be ever ready to approve my ſelf</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honors humble Servant, in the Faith of Chriſt,</hi> Francis Taylor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:63305:4"/>
            <head>The Author to the Chriſtian READER.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>PLace not on earth thy chief delight,</l>
               <l>In which there is more black than white:</l>
               <l>VVho ſet their Hearts on things below,</l>
               <l>And on the World their Thoughts beſtow,</l>
               <l>Of Heavens joy they little know.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Earth's an Impoſtumated Bubble,</l>
               <l>A Map of Miſery and Trouble;</l>
               <l>Our Silver here is mixt with Droſs,</l>
               <l>Our ſweet with ſour, our gain with loſs,</l>
               <l>No comfort here without a croſs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let Heaven be thy Meditation,</l>
               <l>Climbe thither in thy Contemplation;</l>
               <l>VVho ſuch a Pearl have in their eye,</l>
               <l>The worlds Enjoyments by and by</l>
               <l>VVill trample on as Vanity.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:63305:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>No ſeeds of woe are to be found</l>
               <l>I'th' furrows of that holy ground;</l>
               <l>Yea that Caeleſtial Paradiſe</l>
               <l>A ſtranger is to ſin and vice,</l>
               <l>No Serpent there is to entice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>E're Death thy Body in the wombe</l>
               <l>Of Mother-Earth again entombe,</l>
               <l>Be ſure to get an intereſt</l>
               <l>In that prepared place of reſt,</l>
               <l>Whoſe happineſs can't be expreſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Bid Earth adieu, and fix thy Love</l>
               <l>Upon thoſe endleſs joyes above;</l>
               <l>Let no Decoy thy Heart entice,</l>
               <l>But ſtill purſue the Pearl of Price,</l>
               <l>Till thou arrive in Paradiſe.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="invocation">
            <pb facs="tcp:63305:5"/>
            <head>Deo, Opt. Max.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>THou great</hi> Jehovah, <hi>who alone doſt dwell</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In Light, and Glory inacceſſible,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My mind enlighten, help me to unfold</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The glory that thoſe bleſſed ones behold,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>VVho are tranſlated far above the sky,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Into the Region of Eternity.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Inſpire, and actuate my trembling Muſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>VVith heav'nly Raptures, let thy pow'r infuſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Into her, ſuch a rare activity,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That ſhe, above the dreggy earth may fly,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And be ambitious of a glimpſe at leaſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of glory, and the Saints eternal reſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Clear up her pur-blind eye, that ſhe may ſee</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>VVithin the vail, what ever is to be</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Seen by the eye of Faith, and may deſcry</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The bleſſed Manſions in Eternity:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then touch her ſtammering tongue, that ſhe their glory</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>May pencil out with thine own Oratory,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>VVhich beſt befits a ſubject ſo divine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And makes it with the greater luſtre ſhine.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Gordian knot of glory to unty</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>VVould puzzel the acuteſt ingeny.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O let thy wiſdom then, my thoughts direct,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Unveile my dark and clouded intellect.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:63305:6"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Guide my unskilful hand, that ſo I may</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>VVithout a blot, heav'ns happineſs pourtray.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>This is indeed, a mountain too ſublime</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For ſuch an infant Muſe as mine to clime:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yet if thy ſacred ſpirit lead the way</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And me conduct, (for which I humbly pray)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I ſhall adventure, briefly to relate</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And draw a Map, of the eternal ſtate</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of thoſe, who in the fragrant boſome ly,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of ſoul inamouring felicity.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſince this is a task, that doth require</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The lofty aires of an Angelick Lyre;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yea, ſince it is a ſubject ſo profound;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>An Ocean, that no bottom hath, nor bound;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I thee implore (and Lord grant my deſire)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That what I can't expreſs, I may admire.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="encomia">
            <div type="encomium">
               <pb facs="tcp:63305:6"/>
               <head>To his Honored Cozin, Mr. <hi>Francis Taylor,</hi> upon his <hi>Divine Poem.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>—<gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Et Paulo Poſt.</hi> v. 63.
<note place="margin">
                           <bibl>Homer Odyſ. θ. <hi>v.</hi> 43.</bibl>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Ubi forſan ſeipſum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpexiſſe videa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, qua vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gari fama coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus perhibetur.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>What Singer's this the Poet calls for thus?</l>
                  <l>Me thinks <hi>Dear Taylor</hi> thou'rt this <hi>Demodocus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'Tis thine <hi>Urania,</hi> that hath given thee,</l>
                  <l>Inſtead of eyes, this vein of Poeſie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou ſeeſt not Earth, yet pierceſt Heaven, thine eye</l>
                  <l>Is more ſublime, beholds Eternity.</l>
                  <l>The glaring luſters of the world may pleaſe</l>
                  <l>The luſts of ſenſual eyes; but none of theſe</l>
                  <l>Have ought of real Glory in their ſight</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe ſouls are fill'd with a diviner light.</l>
                  <l>This heavenly light adorns thy nobler mind,</l>
                  <l>The world's miſtaken, that accounts thee blind:</l>
                  <l>A veile 'tis true is drawn over thy ſenſe,</l>
                  <l>Yet not without a gracious Providence.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:63305:7"/>
                  <l>For thus thy God hath made the world to thee</l>
                  <l>Known as it is, and what't will ever be,</l>
                  <l>Even darkneſs ſtill. This hath thy glory bin</l>
                  <l>While th' Curtain's drawn without, thou'rt light within.</l>
                  <l>And here thou haſt th' advantage too, while we,</l>
                  <l>That fondly pleaſe our ſelves, and <hi>ſay we ſee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet muſt confeſs, ſo long as day and night</l>
                  <l>Do keep their conſtant turns, darkneſs and light</l>
                  <l>Have their ſucceſſions in us, and that all</l>
                  <l>The light, we have, is but an interval.</l>
                  <l>Theſe changes touch not thee, to whom (we ſay)</l>
                  <l>'Tis ever dark, and yet 'tis ever day.</l>
                  <l>Thy ſoul beholds that glory, and that crown,
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.9.</note> 
                     <hi>VVhich never yet to mortal eye was ſhewen.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So true is that even in Philoſophie,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Tis not the eye, the ſoul alone doth ſee.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thou
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>So are the</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets <hi>called</hi> Seers, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.9.</note> 
                     <hi>ſeeſt</hi> &amp;</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>And</hi> Guides, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 78.72. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.31.—35.</note> 
                     <hi>guideſt</hi> too, that others may</l>
                  <l>By thy <hi>Seraphick</hi> Poem find the way</l>
                  <l>To that caeleſtial throne, yea charm'ſt their cars</l>
                  <l>By this the trueſt <hi>harmony of the ſpheares.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus <hi>Art</hi> doth <hi>Piety</hi> ſweetly greet,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Muſes</hi> and the <hi>Graces</hi> meet.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ovid. Faſtor. l.</hi> 1</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Felices animae, quibus haec cognoſcere primis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Inque domus ſuper as ſcandere cura fuit.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Credibile eſt illos pariter vitiiſque
<note n="*" place="margin">Vulg. <hi>jociſ<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan>
                           </hi> Sic autem cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigenti Doctiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimo <hi>D. Grajo</hi> noſtro luben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffime aſſurgo.</note> lociſque</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Altus humanis exſeruiſſe caput.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Joh. Stileman.</hi> M.A. Paſtor Eccleſiae <hi>Tunbrigignſis</hi> in Agro Cantiano.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="encomium">
               <pb facs="tcp:63305:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To his dear Friend, Mr.</hi> Francis Taylor, <hi>upon his</hi> Grapes from Canaan, &amp;c. <hi>being nocturnal Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations on his Reſtleſs Bed.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>SIght is a bleſſing, God hath made you blind,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yet far more bleſt, in your enlightned mind.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Our pur-blind eyes, which dazle at the glory</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of worldly Objects, fraile and tranſitory,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Allure our minds, to fix their Meditation</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>On earthly Vanities, fond Contemplation!</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Your Eagle light, piercing beyond the sky,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beholds the glory of Eternity,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Height-ning your ſoul, its purer thoughts to place</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>On the rich ſubſtance of immortal Grace.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sleep is a bleſſing, which you cannot find,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yet far more bleſſed in your waking mind.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:63305:8"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Our Nights in ſleeping ſpent, we ſeem to ly</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Among the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ad, beneath the Canopy;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>No thought of God, no Prayers, nor no Praiſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Can ſenſe-bound ſleepers up to Heaven raiſe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Your waking mind, among the Living dwells</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>VVithin the veile, where bleſſedneſs excels,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>VVhere Saints coeleſtial, with Angels ſing,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eternal Praiſe, to the Eternal King.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>VVe ſee thoſe Vines, which in this Deſart grow;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You ſpy that Vine, where Milk and Honey flow;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>VVe Cluſters pluck by Day, but ſowre and tart;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You gather Grapes by Night moſt ſweet, which Art</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Had we obtain'd, though neither ſight; nor reſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yet taſting of ſuch Grapes, we ſhould be bleſt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Clement Barling.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="encomium">
               <pb facs="tcp:63305:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To his dark Friend upon his</hi> Divine Poem <hi>of the Glory of Heaven.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHen God firſt will'd the ſtar-light of thine eyes</l>
                  <l>To ſet, He then commanded to ariſe</l>
                  <l>The Sun-ſhine of his Glory in thy ſoul;</l>
                  <l>And us to ſee how He, without controul,</l>
                  <l>Can bring Light out of Darkneſs, and can make</l>
                  <l>Thy loſs thy gain, thy miſery our miſtake.</l>
                  <l>Wee'l therefore praiſe him for that ſight which He</l>
                  <l>Hath given thee in exchange, and whereby we</l>
                  <l>Do learn, the leſs on earth we fix our eye,</l>
                  <l>The firmer may our hearts be fixt on high.</l>
                  <l>I'have ſometime thought thee blind, but now I ſee</l>
                  <l>'Twas my own thoughts were darkned; as for thee,</l>
                  <l>Thou only hadſt thy ſight a while ſequeſtred,</l>
                  <l>To keep thy higher thoughts from being peſt'red</l>
                  <l>With Earths diverſions; nay, who will not ſay,</l>
                  <l>That reads with care what thou do'ſt here diſplay,</l>
                  <l>But that this thy Divine Apocalyps</l>
                  <l>Doth ſpeak thine eye-ſight only in th' eclipſe</l>
                  <l>By th' interpoſing beams of that great light</l>
                  <l>Above, whoſe glory dazles natures ſight,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:63305:9"/>
                  <l>And bids her wink, that grace a glimpſe may get</l>
                  <l>Of what no eye hath ſeen, nor ear as yet</l>
                  <l>Hath heard, nor is conceiv'd in any heart,</l>
                  <l>Except (as now to thee) reveal'd in part.</l>
                  <l>Henceforth therefore I ſhall not dare to think</l>
                  <l>Thee dark, but only that God bad thee wink</l>
                  <l>A while, till he had taught this froward age</l>
                  <l>To know, not only from what every page</l>
                  <l>Of theſe thy ſpiritual Opticks tells to all,</l>
                  <l>But likewiſe from thy Preaching, and thy Call,</l>
                  <l>That (maugre all ſuch ſpirits as are <hi>freer</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To wreſt, than ſpeak the truth) thou art a <hi>Seer.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Go on then with thy Muſe, let her keep ſight</l>
                  <l>Of what ſhe hath ſpy'd, and follow by the light</l>
                  <l>Of Grace, that ſpirit which taught thy ſoul this ſtory</l>
                  <l>Until thy Grace is ſwallow'd up of Glory.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="encomium">
               <pb facs="tcp:63305:9"/>
               <head>TO Mr. <hi>FRAN. TAYLOR,</hi> ON HIS <hi>Grapes from Canaan.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Taylor,</salute>
               </opener>
               <lg>
                  <l>THou art no Water Poet, not by wine</l>
                  <l>Art thou inſpir'd, thy <hi>genius</hi> is Divine,</l>
                  <l>And ſtoops not to that <hi>Helicon,</hi> thy Quill</l>
                  <l>Soars higher than the proud <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> hill;</l>
                  <l>Thou on the <hi>Holy Mount</hi> above haſt been</l>
                  <l>In Contemplation, and hid things haſt ſeen:</l>
                  <l>Like that ſton'd Martyr <hi>Steven,</hi> we may look,</l>
                  <l>And behold Heaven open'd, in thy Book.</l>
                  <l>Thy blindneſs ſhames, and much out-does our ſight;</l>
                  <l>Our day is dark, and cloudy to thy night:</l>
                  <l>Thy piercing eyes of Faith, and knowledge pry</l>
                  <l>Into thoſe things, that in the vaile do lie.</l>
                  <l>And the third heavens ſecrets look upon</l>
                  <l>Which are the bleſſed Saints rich portion.</l>
                  <l>Thus that choice veſſel <hi>Paul,</hi> his ſight being gone,</l>
                  <l>Did ſee more clearly, and had's viſion.</l>
                  <l>I might thee ſtile the <hi>Homer</hi> of this age,</l>
                  <l>Did not thy richer, and ſublimer page</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:63305:10"/>
                  <l>Forbid, which in its pure and ſacred ſtrain</l>
                  <l>All Boerry (but Fiction) doth contain;</l>
                  <l>Thou only meaſur'd truths doſt tell in that</l>
                  <l>Celeſtial Globe of thine, and heav'nly Map.</l>
                  <l>Let profane Poets looſe and wanton Muſe</l>
                  <l>Be damned to the Grocer's ſervile uſe;</l>
                  <l>Thine is to us more uſeful than a ſtar</l>
                  <l>In Navigation to the Mariner:</l>
                  <l>It ſteels the brow 'gainſt threats, in ſtorms it chears,</l>
                  <l>In dangers comforts, animates in fears,</l>
                  <l>And makes us with a vertuous ſcorn diſdain</l>
                  <l>To yield in Tryals, and count loſſes gain:</l>
                  <l>It doth relieve, although it doth rehearſe</l>
                  <l>(High myſteries) our dulneſs with its verſe.</l>
                  <l>Thus Artiſts ſay, an Emrald ſtanding by</l>
                  <l>In cutting Jewels, helps the weaker eye.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Tho. Woodrooffe,</hi> M. A.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="encomium">
               <pb facs="tcp:63305:10"/>
               <head>TO His Honoured Friend, Mr. <hi>Francis Taylor.</hi> ON HIS <hi>Heavenly Poem.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear Friend,</salute>
               </opener>
               <lg>
                  <l>WEre't not a <hi>Solaetiſme</hi> in Love, I'd ſay</l>
                  <l>Welcome from heav'n (for ſure y'have been that way)</l>
                  <l>But if not ſo, it muſt from <hi>Patmos</hi> be,</l>
                  <l>VVhere you have ſeen Landskip'd-Eternitie.</l>
                  <l>Were <hi>Metempſychoſis</hi> in faſhion now,</l>
                  <l>'Tis probable Saint <hi>John</hi> muſt live in you:</l>
                  <l>Your Book's a Fountain, but the Seals are gon,</l>
                  <l>And all you write is Revelation:</l>
                  <l>VVhich when I read, my ſoul is raviſh'd, and</l>
                  <l>(Like to Religion) doth on <hi>tip-toe</hi> ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Threatning departure in ſweet extaſy,</l>
                  <l>In which I neither truly live, nor dye;</l>
                  <l>And what to <hi>Plato's</hi> Schollar did betide,</l>
                  <l>(Were't not a crime) I could turn <hi>Suicide.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:63305:11"/>
                  <l>But tell me firſt, when you did ſit above,</l>
                  <l>In that high azure <hi>tent,</hi> where ſtars do move,</l>
                  <l>Did not our world look like ſome dirty ſpot?</l>
                  <l>Pray ſay, Could you ſee it, or could you not?</l>
                  <l>How vainly then do moſt by acres gueſs</l>
                  <l>At worth, and miſ call Riches Happineſs!</l>
                  <l>Nay more, when once your Faith was got within</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Empyraean Curtains, where no ſin</l>
                  <l>But ſinners do find place: pray tell me then</l>
                  <l>(Your mem'ry's good I know) what were the men</l>
                  <l>That ſang thoſe holy Notes? Did you not ſee</l>
                  <l>Some Lawn-ſleev'd Saints, and ſome Presbyterie?</l>
                  <l>Did not ſometimes an <hi>Independent ayre,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sometimes a <hi>Baptiſt-Quaker</hi> mingle there?</l>
                  <l>No doubt there did: how fondly then do we</l>
                  <l>Fall out i'th' way, who muſt i'th' End agree!</l>
                  <l>VVe all embrace one fundamental Light,</l>
                  <l>Our hands do joyn, but yet our nails do fight.</l>
                  <l>Come welcome hour, in which my ſun ſhall ſet,</l>
                  <l>And Church-yard graſs ſhall be my Coronet:</l>
                  <l>For who will throw away one Pray'r for Life,</l>
                  <l>VVhen Heav'n ſo calm, and Earth ſo full of ſtrife?</l>
                  <l>VVhen Chriſtendom her fields are now beſpred</l>
                  <l>All o're with killing-troops and with the dead:</l>
                  <l>Like Cannibals our weekly-<hi>Gazets</hi> feed,</l>
                  <l>On purple Broth which dying Chriſtians bleed:</l>
                  <l>As if Baptiſmal water were too faint,</l>
                  <l>And coole an Element to make a ſaint;</l>
                  <l>Our boyſtrous age winds up the Nation high'r</l>
                  <l>And needs muſt be baptiz'd with bloud and fire.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:63305:11"/>
                  <l>For many years Intelligences came</l>
                  <l>Proclaiming wilde-fire from the <hi>Germane</hi> flame,</l>
                  <l>Where kindred-bloud was mingled with the Rhyne,</l>
                  <l>To waſh away th' exceſſes of their wine.</l>
                  <l>And now the ſturdy <hi>Swede</hi> with skilful ſteel</l>
                  <l>Doth let all <hi>Poland</hi> bloud, to make it feel</l>
                  <l>This two-edg'd truth; when God thinks fit to beat,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Luther</hi> ſhall ſtrike as hard as <hi>Mahomet.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But ſtay; theſe lines do run too black: my Pray'r</l>
                  <l>Shall therefore be for <hi>Englands</hi> paſſeover:</l>
                  <l>And while the Maids plant Laurels on your Brow,</l>
                  <l>I'le ſing an <hi>Eulogy</hi> to Faith, and You.</l>
                  <l>Triumphant Faith! How ſtoutly do'ſt thou ſcorn</l>
                  <l>The teſtimony which from ſenſe is born!</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Enoch</hi> by Faith Death's Trophyes did out-brave,</l>
                  <l>And where we fall, he did o're-leap his grave,</l>
                  <l>Still winding up the weights of fleſh ſo high,</l>
                  <l>His body ſtep'd into Eternity.</l>
                  <l>Nought could fore-tel but Faith's Aſtrology,</l>
                  <l>The world debauch'd muſt of a Dropſie dye;</l>
                  <l>But leſt the ſtorm ſhould blow the Globe away,</l>
                  <l>Good <hi>Noah</hi> caſts Faith's anchor out to ſtay</l>
                  <l>The tottring Clod, and in his pinnace ſleeps</l>
                  <l>VVhere all the ſeminals of life he keeps.</l>
                  <l>By this when <hi>Sarah</hi> in her wrinckls lay,</l>
                  <l>And all her white and red did fade away,</l>
                  <l>VVhen ſnow was all the locks ſhe wore, then ſhe</l>
                  <l>Dandled by Faith her <hi>Iſaac</hi> on her knee.</l>
                  <l>Faiths Bull-ruſh 'twas kept <hi>Moſes</hi> like a ſwan</l>
                  <l>On <hi>Nilus</hi> lapp, and when he was grown man</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:63305:12"/>
                  <l>He foild the guilded-dangers of a court,</l>
                  <l>And made dry paths where <hi>whales</hi> were wont to ſport.</l>
                  <l>And leſt ſome Atheiſt, ſhould in <hi>Sarcaſmes</hi> ſay</l>
                  <l>Faith then was young, but now ſhee's weak &amp; gray:</l>
                  <l>Behold a Chriſtian <hi>Homer</hi> without eyes</l>
                  <l>By Faith out-ſees two Univerſities.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>William Jacob,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="encomium">
               <pb facs="tcp:63305:12"/>
               <head>TO His Honoured Friend, Mr. <hi>Francis Taylor,</hi> Upon His <hi>Grapes from Canaan;</hi> OR, <hi>The Believers preſent taſte of future glory.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>AWake my Muſe, take up thy Lyre,</l>
                  <l>And make one of this ſacred quire;</l>
                  <l>Who would not gladly ſhow his art</l>
                  <l>VVhere ev'ry creature adds its part?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Mark how the Birds do ſweetly frame</l>
                  <l>Their Voice to blaze their Makers fame!</l>
                  <l>Hark how they chirp and flock together,</l>
                  <l>Provoking to this work each other!</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:63305:13"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVho, though with much alacrity</l>
                  <l>They all proclaim a Deity,</l>
                  <l>None to ſo high a Note can riſe</l>
                  <l>As this rare Bird of Paradiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou art the <hi>Orpheus</hi> of our age</l>
                  <l>Whoſe quill, when ſtorms within do rage,</l>
                  <l>With ſuch ſweet noiſe doth fill our ear</l>
                  <l>As can't be told by thoſe that hear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy lines, thy words, and ev'ry letter</l>
                  <l>Are ſo well ſuited to thy matter,</l>
                  <l>That from King <hi>David</hi> I'le defend it,</l>
                  <l>Thou mayſt be lineally deſcended.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He of the Earthly City wrot,</l>
                  <l>To praiſe the Heavenly is thy Plot;</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe glory doth ſo ſhine in thee</l>
                  <l>Though blind thou can'ſt not chuſe but ſee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When once the Soul hath fix't its eye</l>
                  <l>Upon the Glorie of things on high,</l>
                  <l>And ſeen its Chriſt within the vaile,</l>
                  <l>What matter though the Body's faile.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:63305:13"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Haſte then my Soul! VVith this good guide</l>
                  <l>Haſte to that Glory here deſcri'd;</l>
                  <l>Thou need'ſt not fear to go aſtray,</l>
                  <l>VVhen this great Seer leads the way.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVhere Angels and where Seraphim,</l>
                  <l>VVhere bleſſed Saints and Cherubin,</l>
                  <l>Praiſes continually do ſing</l>
                  <l>To God, our God, and heavenly King.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Frederick Primroſe.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="grc" type="encomium">
               <pb facs="tcp:63305:14"/>
               <head>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="encomium">
               <pb facs="tcp:63305:14"/>
               <head>Amico ſuo ingenioſiſſimo celeberrimi hujus Poematis Authori merito hoc en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comiaſticon commendat <hi>N.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Philo-Porta.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>REgia marmoreis pluſquam fabricata columnis</l>
                  <l>Celſa Dei eſt, ſeſe extendens per inane locorum;</l>
                  <l>Lucidior gemmis; Chryſtallo purior omni</l>
                  <l>Conſpicuo, longe fulvo rutilantior auro:</l>
                  <l>Firmior &amp; domibus multo fluitantibus orbis;</l>
                  <l>Nomina, cum titulis, nec non adjuncta ſacratis,</l>
                  <l>Hujus coeleſtis Paradiſi, conſuis ipſe haec</l>
                  <l>Omnia Taylere inſignis. Beatifica dona,</l>
                  <l>Fulgoris radiis complentia corpora pura,</l>
                  <l>Ut<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſigillatim memores! Ut agilia narres!</l>
                  <l>Non moritura unquam! Forma nitidiſſima! Nec non</l>
                  <l>(Attributa quidem haec!) incompatibilia! Deinde</l>
                  <l>Lux, &amp; felicitas animarum clara ſacrarum;</l>
                  <l>Cognitio ſcilicet gemmans, dominum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> amor erga</l>
                  <l>Seſe &amp; perfectus, collucent verſibus aptis.</l>
                  <l>Haectua depinxit graphice pia, docta Camaena;</l>
                  <l>(Dulcis Amice) ſtylum poliit tua lima Britannum,</l>
                  <l>Carmine ſuaviſono; ſcandant ſuper aethera laudes.</l>
                  <l>Non torrem oſtendam ſoli; mea Muſa ſileſcet</l>
                  <l>More Timanthaeo obvolvens haec ardua nube.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="encomium">
               <pb facs="tcp:63305:15"/>
               <head>To my Loving Friend, Mr. <hi>Fran. Taylor,</hi> upon his excellent <hi>Poem,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>Grapes from Canaan, &amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>DEpriv'd of ſight can he be ſaid to be</l>
                  <l>Who ſees the light? How true is this of thee!</l>
                  <l>Thy ſoul is full of eyes, whoſe ſight refin'd</l>
                  <l>See far, although thou bodily art blind.</l>
                  <l>Let this to none a Paradox appear</l>
                  <l>That thou a blind-man art, and yet a <hi>Seer.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Paul</hi> was wrap't up into the heavens third ſtory:</l>
                  <l>So thou, which made thee limne ſo well its glory.</l>
                  <l>Thy skill hath made Objects remote t' appear</l>
                  <l>Cloſe by; and things a diſtance off ſeem neer.</l>
                  <l>Sin is alas! an interpoſing ſcreen,</l>
                  <l>A ſeparating wall, which ſtands between</l>
                  <l>Glory and us; but by thine heavenly art</l>
                  <l>Glory's revealed unto us in part.</l>
                  <l>Thine underſtandings ſearch hath brought to light</l>
                  <l>Secrets abſtruſe; O blindneſs bleſt for ſight!</l>
                  <l>The Spaniards Dove <hi>Columbus,</hi> and our <hi>Drake,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Not Quaking in the leaſt) did undertake</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:63305:15"/>
                  <l>A long, and dang'rous voyage; ſayling over</l>
                  <l>Remoteſt Seas, new Ilands to diſcover.</l>
                  <l>Home they return, their richer veſſels hold</l>
                  <l>A fraught of nought, but glorious luggage Gold.</l>
                  <l>Had they both <hi>Indies,</hi> and could <hi>Numid</hi>-like</l>
                  <l>Meaſure their unſumm'd treaſure by a ſtrike;</l>
                  <l>Time would conſume it; what a thief is Chink?</l>
                  <l>The greateſt baggs will in the uſing ſhrink.</l>
                  <l>Alas! alas! the Glory they did win</l>
                  <l>Was earthly, vain; their Bullion falling in</l>
                  <l>A deep conſumption, pin'd away by leaſure;</l>
                  <l>See there the end of their laborious pleaſure!</l>
                  <l>But as for thee (my truly Honor'd Friend)</l>
                  <l>Thou Rigg'ſt thy Veſſel for an other end.</l>
                  <l>Thy braver ſpirit doth with ſcorn diſdain</l>
                  <l>The roaming here, upon the foaming Main.</l>
                  <l>Grace is the Ship, thy ſoul doth go aboard;</l>
                  <l>Thy Faith's the Sayl, thy Steers-man is Gods Word;</l>
                  <l>His Spirit's the Wind, that drives thee by degrees</l>
                  <l>O're the calm back of th' <hi>Erythraean</hi> ſeas,</l>
                  <l>I mean Chriſt's bloud: thou tak'ſt a view of heaven,</l>
                  <l>Returneſt richly fraught with Jewels, given</l>
                  <l>By God himſelf; by doing good thou thriv'ſt,</l>
                  <l>Thy lands enrich'd; this is the trade thou driv'ſt.</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Noahs</hi> Dove, thou canſt not, doſt not ceaſe,</l>
                  <l>Until thou bringſt an Olive-branch of Peace.</l>
                  <l>Wouldſt thou view heaven on earth (kind <hi>Reader</hi>) then</l>
                  <l>Let thine eye trace the foot-ſteps of his pen</l>
                  <l>Steer'd by an others hand; be pleas'd to look</l>
                  <l>On the Reflections of this precious Book:</l>
                  <l>And here it is, heavens glorious Objects paſs</l>
                  <l>Unto Faiths eye, through this proſpective glaſs.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:63305:16"/>
                  <l>Doſt thou deſire with beauties moſt ſublime</l>
                  <l>T'enrich thy ſoul, engarriſon'd with ſlime?</l>
                  <l>Shake off Earths dangling fetters which keep down</l>
                  <l>Thy lab'ring ſoul from riſing to its Crown.</l>
                  <l>The tranſient pleaſures of this Mole-hill Earth,</l>
                  <l>Afford at beſt but melancholy mirth:</l>
                  <l>But joyes in heaven, which are only ſure</l>
                  <l>And ſtable, ſhall eternally endure</l>
                  <l>In ſpight of time; there the bleſ'd Saints advance</l>
                  <l>Their heightned notes above the reach of chance.</l>
                  <l>Be practically good; bid ſin good-b'wy,</l>
                  <l>And Glory's thine, I'le warrant you; I, I,</l>
                  <l>'Tis thine, 'tis thine; the heavens have decreed</l>
                  <l>It thine, it thine. <hi>Beatitude indeed!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Wouldſt thou be made one of the royal ſtem,</l>
                  <l>And Den'ſon of the <hi>New-Jeruſalem?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Be ſure thou follow this directive way,</l>
                  <l>And then thou wilt not, nay, thou canſt not ſtray.</l>
                  <l>Heav'n ſhield us all from the worlds Philtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charms,</l>
                  <l>And hold us faſt in his encircling arms;</l>
                  <l>O may we ever in that Glory reſt,</l>
                  <l>Which our rare Author ſweetly hath expreſt!</l>
                  <l>Thrice happy be that ſoul, who (thirſting) gapes</l>
                  <l>To drink this liquor, preſt from <hi>Canaans Grapes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Canterbury,</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>July</hi> 1. 1657.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Nicholas Billingsley.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:63305:16"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Believers preſent taſte of future glory</hi> Page 1</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Heavens glory not to be fully dsplaid in this life</hi> Page 3</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Heavens Glory ſet out by</hi> 6 <hi>Properties</hi> Page 8
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Its Altitude ibid</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Its Magnificence</hi> Page 10</item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Its Purity</hi> Page 12</item>
                     <item>4 <hi>Its Amplitude</hi> Page 14</item>
                     <item>5 <hi>Its Brightneſs ibid</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6 <hi>Its Permanency</hi> Page 16</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Heavens glory further ſet out by ſundry Scripture-names, titles &amp; epithites, as</hi> Page 18
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>A Kingdom</hi> Page 19</item>
                     <item>2 A <hi>Heavenly Kingdom</hi> Page 20</item>
                     <item>3 <hi>The Kingdom of God ibid</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4 <hi>An Inheritance</hi> Page 21</item>
                     <item>5 <hi>An incorruptible Inheritance ibid</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6 <hi>An exceeding &amp; eternal weight of glory</hi> Page 22</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Saints ſhall be with Chriſt in heaven</hi> Page 24</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>They ſhall be all Kings</hi> Page 29</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>They ſhall be all filled with joy</hi> Page 31</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>They ſhall have perfect Reſt</hi> Page 34</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>They ſhall have full Security</hi> Page 36</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>There ſhall be a vindication of their names</hi> Page 39</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Their Graces ſhall be perfected</hi> Page 42</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:63305:17"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Beauty and Bleſſedneſs of Glorified Bodres</hi> Page 44
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>They are Immortal</hi> Page 46</item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Impaſſible</hi> Page 48</item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Agile</hi> Page 49</item>
                     <item>4 <hi>Amtable</hi> Page 51</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Beauty and Bleſſedneſs of Glorified Souls</hi> Page 52
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Their Knowledge perfected</hi> Page 53</item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Their Love perfected</hi> Page 59</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Five Practical Concluſions</hi> Page 64</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Four Marks of our Intereſt in Heaven</hi> Page 75</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A General Concluſion</hi> Page 82</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Faiths Triumph</hi> Page 86</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>In page 3. line 5. for <hi>the comprehenſible,</hi> r. <hi>th' incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible:</hi> p. 17. l. 9. for <hi>man</hi> r. <hi>men:</hi> p. 31. l. 5. for <hi>joyn'd</hi> r. <hi>joyned.</hi> p. 40. l. 27. for <hi>ſtiled</hi> r. <hi>ſtil'd.</hi> p. 47. l. 2. for <hi>our</hi> r. <hi>over.</hi> p. 49. l. 21. for <hi>at</hi> r. <hi>it.</hi> p. 51. l. 15. r. <hi>bodies.</hi> p. 62. l. 9. r. <hi>keep.</hi> p. 62. l. 16. r. <hi>wound.</hi> p, 71. l. 13. r. <hi>makes.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63305:17"/>
            <head>GRAPES FROM CANAAN. OR, The <hi>Believers</hi> preſent <hi>taſte</hi> OF Future Glory.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THe lives of Saints are <hi>Tragae-comaedies;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Their future joy, their preſent grief out-vies:</l>
               <l>Their death is ſweet, although their life be ſowr,</l>
               <l>Tears in the bud, but Glory in the flower.</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:63305:18"/>
               <l>The bleſſed Angels at the port of bliſs,</l>
               <l>Or portal of the Heavenly edifice,</l>
               <l>As Maſters of the Ceremonies ſtand,</l>
               <l>To welcome Saints into the <hi>Holy Land:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From whence into their Fathers Court ſtrait-way</l>
               <l>Theſe <hi>Miniſtring Spirits</hi> their new-Gueſts convey.</l>
               <l>The glory that the Bleſſed there behold</l>
               <l>All language is too narrow to unfold:</l>
               <l>The glittering ſtars, which in that Orbe do ſhine,</l>
               <l>No Logick can ſufficiently define.</l>
               <l>Had I as many tongues as hairs, yet I</l>
               <l>Could never ſet out the reſplendency</l>
               <l>Of that celeſtial Paradiſe above,</l>
               <l>For ſaints ordained by the God of Love;</l>
               <l>The ſhadow of it in the picture I</l>
               <l>Can only give, and that imperfectly.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:63305:18"/>
               <head>Heavens Glory not to be fully diſplai'd in this life.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>NO eye hath ſeen, ear heard, or heart of man</l>
                  <l>At any time conceived hath, or can</l>
                  <l>The comprehenſible ſublimity</l>
                  <l>And glorious myſteries of that moſt high</l>
                  <l>And heavenly Wiſdom, and unparallel'd</l>
                  <l>Sweetneſs, which in the Goſpel is reveai'd:</l>
                  <l>How altogether then unutterable</l>
                  <l>Is the perfection, how inexplicable</l>
                  <l>The full, the real, and the actual</l>
                  <l>Fruition of thoſe Evangelical</l>
                  <l>Myſterious Revelations, which are even</l>
                  <l>Accompliſh'd to the height in th' higheſt Heaven.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The eye of man hath ſeen Earths rareſt ſights,</l>
                  <l>Its braveſt Ornaments, and chief delights;</l>
                  <l>Mountains of Chryſtal, and rich Mines of Gold,</l>
                  <l>With Rocks of Diamonds, wondrous to behold,</l>
                  <l>Ilands of Spices, and the Pearly coaſt,</l>
                  <l>(Of which ſome Travellers ſo much do boaſt)</l>
                  <l>The ſtately and ſublime Pyramides,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Diana</hi>'s Temple, and ſuch like as theſe,</l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:63305:19"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mauſolus</hi> tombe in all its pompe and pride,</l>
                  <l>With all the wonders of the world beſide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Ear hath with the ſweeteſt melody</l>
                  <l>Oft charmed been, even with ſuch harmony,</l>
                  <l>As once tranſported the amazed ear</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Alexander</hi> with a pang (as 't were)</l>
                  <l>Of pleaſing rage, and ſweerly did inhance</l>
                  <l>His ſpirit with a moſt delightful dance.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Heart of man imagine and ſurmiſe</l>
                  <l>Rare pieces can, and ſtrange felicities;</l>
                  <l>The pebbles on the ground it in conceit</l>
                  <l>Into rich Pearls can <hi>tranſubſtantiate;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Duſt into ſilver, into liquid Oare</l>
                  <l>The Land encircling Ocean, nay more</l>
                  <l>With greater beauty it and ſweetneſs can</l>
                  <l>The boſome of Dame Nature garniſh, than</l>
                  <l>The eye e're ſaw, each ſtar into a ſun</l>
                  <l>It can convert, and when it ſo hath done,</l>
                  <l>Can make thoſe ſuns far bigger and more bright,</l>
                  <l>Than that which gilds the heaven with its light.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And yet the height of Evangelical</l>
                  <l>Wiſdome out-ſhines, and far ſurpaſſeth all</l>
                  <l>That eye, ear, or the heart of men could ever</l>
                  <l>See, hear, or know, though heightned with endeavor:</l>
                  <l>And this ſo rare, and admirable light</l>
                  <l>On Earth, diſcovering unto our ſight</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:63305:19"/>
                  <l>The treaſures of Caeleſtial and Divine</l>
                  <l>Wiſdome in Chriſt, is to the richeſt Mine</l>
                  <l>Of Gold, but as a grain; yea, leſſer than</l>
                  <l>A drop of water to the Ocean.</l>
                  <l>When with theſe ſempiternal joyes above</l>
                  <l>It is compar'd which by the God of Love</l>
                  <l>For thoſe ordain'd are, that have ſtricken ſayl,</l>
                  <l>And ſafely landed are within the vayl.</l>
                  <l>Oh then how far! How far bayond all meaſure</l>
                  <l>Doth the ſublimity of heavens pleaſure</l>
                  <l>Tranſcend the moſt enlarg'd capacity</l>
                  <l>Of men? For humane knowledge 'tis too high.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is a Fruit of our unhappy Fall</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Adam,</hi> and the ſad Eſtate of all</l>
                  <l>That ſo journe in this vale of miſery</l>
                  <l>To know heavens glory but imperfectly:</l>
                  <l>From which our clearer and compleater knowledge,</l>
                  <l>When we 're admitted into <hi>Zion Colledge</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall differ, as a little Infants doth</l>
                  <l>From his who is arriv'd at perfect growth.</l>
                  <l>As knowledge by a glaſs from apprehenſion</l>
                  <l>Of real objects, till the great convention,</l>
                  <l>That fulneſſe we of light can't pierce, nor pry</l>
                  <l>Into the bottomleſſe profundity</l>
                  <l>Of endleſſe joyes, nor in that brightneſſe dwell,</l>
                  <l>Which is to mortals unapproachable:</l>
                  <l>This is reſerved to the day of Doom,</l>
                  <l>When Jeſus Chriſt the Spouſes lovely Groom</l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:63305:20"/>
                  <l>Shall her conduct into his Fathers tent,</l>
                  <l>And without ſpot, her there to him preſent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our Intellects upon neceſſity</l>
                  <l>Irradiated ſupernaturally,</l>
                  <l>Muſt be with extraordinary light,</l>
                  <l>Ere they can have a clear and perfect ſight</l>
                  <l>Of future bliſs, or fully comprehend</l>
                  <l>The brightneſs of thoſe joyes, which know no end.</l>
                  <l>It is as eaſie for a mortal man,</l>
                  <l>the Globe of Earth to compaſs with a ſpan,</l>
                  <l>Or in a Nut-ſhell the Ocean to contain,</l>
                  <l>As to deſcribe exactly every vein</l>
                  <l>Of Heavens Golden Mine—</l>
                  <l>Philoſophers of old could ſay that even</l>
                  <l>As Owles eyes are to th' ſhining Lamp of Heaven;</l>
                  <l>So are the ſharpeſt and moſt piercing eyes</l>
                  <l>Of pregnant wits to Natures myſteries:</l>
                  <l>Oh then! How ſtrangely would they dazled be,</l>
                  <l>And even ſtruck ſtark blind, ſhould they but ſee</l>
                  <l>The ſparkling luſtre, and exceſſive height</l>
                  <l>Of Heavens ſecrets, and immortal light?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But though the whole we cannot fully know,</l>
                  <l>Yet part we may conſider here below;</l>
                  <l>Although of that o're-flowing Fountain we</l>
                  <l>Can't have a full draught, yet a taſte may be</l>
                  <l>Attain'd on Earth, though the whole Harveſt can't</l>
                  <l>Be here enjoy'd by th' moſt ſublimed Saint;</l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:63305:20"/>
                  <l>Yet of the firſt-Fruits we a brief ſurvey</l>
                  <l>May take; the Scriptures to this end diſplay</l>
                  <l>And ſhadow out a glympſe, by things that are</l>
                  <l>Eſteemed here moſt excellent and rare.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:63305:21"/>
               <head>HEAVENS GLORY Set out by its PROPERTIES.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe Glory of the <hi>Saints eternal reſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May by its <hi>Properties</hi> be well expreſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Heavens Altitude.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THat bleſſed place which Saints by Faith deſcry,</l>
                     <l>Is ſet out by a mountain great and high:</l>
                     <l>It hath its ſcituation far above</l>
                     <l>The Sun and ſtars, which in their Orbs do move,</l>
                     <l>Above thoſe glorious Luminaries, which</l>
                     <l>With beams of light this lower-world enrich:</l>
                     <l>In power and pride are worldlings oft-times high,</l>
                     <l>And though they could their Neſts build in the sky,</l>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:63305:21"/>
                     <l>So firmly, that they thought none could remove them,</l>
                     <l>Yet ſhal the ſaints be ſhortly far above them:</l>
                     <l>Their Eagle on his ſacred wings ſhall bear</l>
                     <l>Them far above the Element of fear.</l>
                     <l>Their proper houſe and place of reſt is even</l>
                     <l>Where Chriſt is in the Empyrean Heaven;</l>
                     <l>A City whoſe aſpiring walls deſie</l>
                     <l>The ſcaling Ladders of the Enemy.</l>
                     <l>A Fort erected far above the skies,</l>
                     <l>That's too too ſtrong for humane batteries;</l>
                     <l>A Caſtle reared on a towring Rock,</l>
                     <l>No ſilver Key can ever it unlock:</l>
                     <l>It fears no underminings, and the ſhot</l>
                     <l>Of malice, it is far above (I wor.)</l>
                     <l>The arrows which are up againſt it ſent,</l>
                     <l>Do with redoubled force rebound, and rent</l>
                     <l>The hairy ſcalps of thoſe who let them fly</l>
                     <l>From off the ſtring ſo inconſid'rately.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:63305:22"/>
                  <head>Heavens Magnificence.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>IF all the Architects on Earth ſhould ſtrive,</l>
                     <l>And lay their heads together to contrive</l>
                     <l>A ſtately Palace, and had all the gems,</l>
                     <l>And precious ſtones in Princes Diadems;</l>
                     <l>Yea, all the Diamonds in the world to ſet</l>
                     <l>Into it, and to beautifie it, yet</l>
                     <l>It would be doubtleſs in compariſon,</l>
                     <l>To Heaven but a darkſome dungeon.</l>
                     <l>The Porch of that celeſtial Habitation</l>
                     <l>Doth fill the minds of men with admiration.</l>
                     <l>Our dazelled eyes unable are to pry</l>
                     <l>Into the beauty of th' enamel'd sky.</l>
                     <l>All precious ſtones when laid together, are</l>
                     <l>Not ſo refulgent as one ſingle ſtar.</l>
                     <l>What glory in the Preſence Chamber then</l>
                     <l>Shall Saints amaze, when they are from the den,</l>
                     <l>And cave of Earth advanc'd above the sky,</l>
                     <l>To reign in Heaven to eternity!</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fulgentius</hi> eying well the Senate Houſe</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Rome,</hi> which was exceeding glorious,</l>
                     <l>Did both its bulk and bravery contemne,</l>
                     <l>As nothing to the <hi>New Jeruſalem.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:63305:22"/>
                     <l>That Cities pavement is of Gold moſt pure,</l>
                     <l>What are the Hangings then and Furniture?</l>
                     <l>How Orient are thoſe Jewels which are ſet</l>
                     <l>Into the frame of that rare Cabinet?</l>
                     <l>Thoſe rarities on Earth which oft invite</l>
                     <l>Our eyes, and raviſh them with much delight,</l>
                     <l>Appear but vile and fordid in their eyes,</l>
                     <l>Who with a ſight of heavens embroideries</l>
                     <l>Made happy are: a glorious place no doubt</l>
                     <l>It is, where God doth all his coſt lay out:</l>
                     <l>It needs muſt be a ſtately Fabrick, where</l>
                     <l>Wiſdom contrives, and Bounty doth not ſpare.</l>
                     <l>In heaven (as we read in ſacred ſtory)</l>
                     <l>There is a kingdom, crowns, thrones, weight of glory,</l>
                     <l>Now wonder 'tis to me the violent</l>
                     <l>Take heaven by force, 'tis ſo magnificent.</l>
                     <l>I marvel more that many Chriſtians are</l>
                     <l>No more contentious in this Holy War.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:63305:23"/>
                  <head>Heavens Purity.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>IN <hi>Purity</hi> this bleſſed ſoyle doth paſſe</l>
                     <l>Refined Gold, and moſt tranſparent Glaſſe.</l>
                     <l>Its Emblem'd by the ſaphire ſtone, which hath</l>
                     <l>A precious vertue in't (as <hi>Pliny</hi> ſaith)</l>
                     <l>Purity to preſerve, none thither come</l>
                     <l>Stain'd with the births of ſins too pregnant womb.</l>
                     <l>Sometimes again 'tis repreſented by</l>
                     <l>The ſparkling Em'rald whoſe rare quality</l>
                     <l>Is poyſon to expel, heaven is ſo pure</l>
                     <l>That ſin and ſinners it will not endure.</l>
                     <l>That air is from malignant vapours freed,</l>
                     <l>No Viper of corruption there doth breed.</l>
                     <l>The Serpent which to ſin did man intice,</l>
                     <l>Was long ſince caſt out of that Paradiſe.</l>
                     <l>There no aſſaults of ſinful on-ſets are,</l>
                     <l>When once a ſpotleſs ſoul, a virgin ſtar</l>
                     <l>Hath in that Orbe caeleſtial its ſtation,</l>
                     <l>It need not fear the rape of a temptation,</l>
                     <l>Upon that ſacred ſtage ſin acts no part,</l>
                     <l>The Eyes are there no Panders to the Heart.</l>
                     <l>No ſinful tinctures there of inquination</l>
                     <l>Be ſpeckle ſhall the choſen generation.</l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:63305:23"/>
                     <l>No Feaver there of Luſt is to be found,</l>
                     <l>All Vice is baniſh'd from that holy ground.</l>
                     <l>Indeed on Earth of ſin few ſtand in awe,</l>
                     <l>Men ſet up Wickedneſſe oft by a Law.</l>
                     <l>And wicked men devour (O cruel Elves!)</l>
                     <l>Their neighbors, far more righteous than themſelves.</l>
                     <l>Here Juſt ones are maligned, 'cauſe they 're juſt</l>
                     <l>And won't be Bandogs to ſome great ones luſt.</l>
                     <l>More Juſtice there in the infernal Den</l>
                     <l>Is to be found, than 'mong the ſons of men.</l>
                     <l>Hell doth oppreſs none that are innocent,</l>
                     <l>But here 'gainſt righteouſneſs the world is bent.</l>
                     <l>Holineſs is the White, at which the Divol</l>
                     <l>His fiery Darts doth principally level.</l>
                     <l>But Heaven is a place of Equity,</l>
                     <l>No wronged perſons there for Juſtice cry;</l>
                     <l>There are (as ſacred Scriptures do expreſs)</l>
                     <l>The Sun, the Robe, the Crown of Righteouſneſs.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:63305:24"/>
                  <head>Heavens Amplitude.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>SPacious enough that Heavenly ſtructure is,</l>
                     <l>To entertain the ſouls ordain'd to bliſs.</l>
                     <l>It is a Garner wide enough to hold,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe bleſſed Grains whoſe number can't be told.</l>
                     <l>How ample is the <hi>New Jeruſalem?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Where every Saint's deck'd with a Diadem.</l>
                     <l>Though myriads of Saints inhabit there,</l>
                     <l>Yet every Saint doth move in his own ſphere.</l>
                     <l>'Tis not a place ſo narrow or ſo ſtrait,</l>
                     <l>But ſublime ſpirits may there expatiate.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Heavens Brightneſs.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THat Royal Palace which excels in height,</l>
                     <l>Is called an inheritance in light;</l>
                     <l>The ſplendor of it doth the Sun's out vie,</l>
                     <l>It far ſurpaſſes its reſplendency.</l>
                     <l>Were every ſtar a ſun, without all doubt,</l>
                     <l>Heavens luſtre they could never ſhadow out.</l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:63305:24"/>
                     <l>Light is a glorious creature, what were all</l>
                     <l>The world, if Darkneſs ſhould the ſame enthral?</l>
                     <l>Alas! What beauty is there in the ſun,</l>
                     <l>When it is vayl'd, and hath a muffler on?</l>
                     <l>Light actuates the colours, and doth ſhew,</l>
                     <l>Each Herb and Flower in its moſt verdant hew.</l>
                     <l>'Tis Natures ſmile, the Univerſes gloſs,</l>
                     <l>Who wants the light, doth need no greater croſs,</l>
                     <l>Light beautifies the creatures with its rayes,</l>
                     <l>It is on bodies a bright paraphraſe.</l>
                     <l>Whether i'th modeſty of a morning bluſh</l>
                     <l>It ſelf it doth diſcover, or doth ruſh</l>
                     <l>In with more ſpriteful beams, whither in a ſtar</l>
                     <l>It twinckles, or doth in a Comet glare;</l>
                     <l>Whither in a Gem it frisketh in the night,</l>
                     <l>Or in a Glow-worm playes the hypocrite.</l>
                     <l>Whither in a Lamp it doth epitomize</l>
                     <l>It ſelf, or in a ſpark it ſelf comprize.</l>
                     <l>How e're 'tis pleaſed it ſelf to manifeſt,</l>
                     <l>Or in what form ſoever it is dreſt,</l>
                     <l>Such a commanding luſtre in its face</l>
                     <l>It alwayes carries, as it ſelf doth grace:</l>
                     <l>Yet O how dark doth Light it ſelf appear,</l>
                     <l>When to the fountain it of Light drawes near?</l>
                     <l>The place of reſt that in the world to come,</l>
                     <l>Remains for ſaints, is a <hi>diaphanum.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>It is not like the Element o're head</l>
                     <l>That's here and there with ſtars enammelled,</l>
                     <l>No, 'tis a Body wonderfully bright,</l>
                     <l>Being all o're embroidered with light.</l>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:63305:25"/>
                     <l>The glory of the Sun is needleſs there,</l>
                     <l>Chriſt is the Sun that ſhineth in that ſphere.</l>
                     <l>A Sun that no Eclipſe can over-ſhrowd,</l>
                     <l>A Sun that can't be masked with a cloud.</l>
                     <l>A Sun which riſing on the ſaints that reign,</l>
                     <l>With God in glory, never ſets again:</l>
                     <l>Whenas the ſacred ſcriptures would expreſs,</l>
                     <l>The glorious majeſty, and bleſſedneſs</l>
                     <l>Of God himſelf, unto the very height,</l>
                     <l>They make 't conſiſt in this, He dwells in light.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Heavens Permanency.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>HEaven is a place ſubject to no decay,</l>
                     <l>An Heritage that fadeth not away;</l>
                     <l>No wonder ſaints are with it ſo much taken,</l>
                     <l>It is a Kingdom that cannot be ſhaken.</l>
                     <l>The great and mighty Monarchies on earth,</l>
                     <l>Have had their dying times as well as birth;</l>
                     <l>Their ruins were as certain as their riſe,</l>
                     <l>But as for the Celeſtial paradiſe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Venices
<note n="*" place="margin">Nec fluctu, nec fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetur.</note> Motto</hi> you may on it write,</l>
                     <l>No winds nor waves can ſtir't with al their might.</l>
                     <l>The tabernacle, wch was tranſient,</l>
                     <l>Did tranſitory comforts repreſent.</l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:63305:25"/>
                     <l>But Heavens joy and happineſs (no doubt)</l>
                     <l>Were by the fixed temple ſhadow'd out:</l>
                     <l>The ſaints ſhall bath themſelves in bliſs for ever,</l>
                     <l>Nothing ſhall them and their Redeemer ſever.</l>
                     <l>Their Leaſe of Heaven perpetual ſhall be,</l>
                     <l>Stamp'd with the broad ſeal of Eternitie.</l>
                     <l>Eternity's a Day that hath no Night;</l>
                     <l>A Spring that hath no Autumne, joy at height:</l>
                     <l>O happy man, who being freed from thrall,</l>
                     <l>Enjoy the viſion beatifical!</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:63305:26"/>
               <head>HEAVENS GLORY FURTHER SHADOWED OUT BY ITS <hi>NAMES, TITLES,</hi> AND <hi>EPITHITES.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe <hi>Titles, Names,</hi> and <hi>Epithites,</hi> that are</l>
                  <l>Aſcrib'd to Heavenly joyes, do yet declare,</l>
                  <l>And further to our reliſh repreſent,</l>
                  <l>Their ſweetneſs, even to aſtoniſhment.</l>
               </lg>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:63305:26"/>
                  <head>A Kingdom.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>HEaven is a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and a Kingly throne</l>
                     <l>Is held the top, crown, and perfection</l>
                     <l>Of ſublunary bliſs, the higheſt aime</l>
                     <l>Of mans ambition, that which doth inflame</l>
                     <l>His aſpiration moſt, a confluence</l>
                     <l>It is of Riches and magnificence,</l>
                     <l>Of glory, pompe, and royal majeſty,</l>
                     <l>Of pleaſure and delightful bravery;</l>
                     <l>Or what the heart of man can more deſire,</l>
                     <l>To make his outward happineſs entire:</l>
                     <l>What ſtirs and ſtratagems, what pulling down,</l>
                     <l>Of one another, to climbe to a crown?</l>
                     <l>What <hi>Machavillian</hi> depths, what ſtrange adventures?</l>
                     <l>What ſtretching of mens brains upon the tenters?</l>
                     <l>What cunning Plots, what rowling of each ſtone,</l>
                     <l>To be inſtalled in the regal throne?</l>
                     <l>Witneſs our <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> nay all</l>
                     <l>Earths habitable parts both great and ſmall,</l>
                     <l>Which have from time to time prov'd (as we find</l>
                     <l>In ſtory) bloody Cock-pits in this kind.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:63305:27"/>
                  <head>An heavenly Kingdom.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>AN Heavenly Kingdom</hi> 'tis to intimate,</l>
                     <l>That it in excellency, pompe, and ſtate,</l>
                     <l>As far tranſcends all earthly Kingdoms, as</l>
                     <l>The Empyrean Heaven doth ſurpaſs</l>
                     <l>The Earth with all its bravery and ſtore</l>
                     <l>Of choice delights, and infinitely more.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Kingdom of God.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>GOds Kingdom,</hi> 'tis a Kingdom of his own</l>
                     <l>Framing and beautifying; 'tis a throne</l>
                     <l>Erected by his power, who like himſelf</l>
                     <l>Doth all things make, not deek'd with worldly pelt,</l>
                     <l>But with ineffable tranſcendencies</l>
                     <l>Embelliſh'd, and ſuch rare felicities,</l>
                     <l>As beſt beſeem the Maker of all things,</l>
                     <l>The glorious reſidence of the King of Kings.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:63305:27"/>
                  <head>An Inheritance.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>IT is no <hi>tenement</hi> at will, to be</l>
                     <l>Poſſeſt or left at th'Landlords libertie:</l>
                     <l>But <hi>an Inheritance</hi> to us convey'd,</l>
                     <l>And ſeal'd by th' higheſt price that e're was paid.</l>
                     <l>Which will as orient and as pretious be,</l>
                     <l>After as many thouſand years as we</l>
                     <l>Can poſſibly conceive, as 'twas the firſt</l>
                     <l>Day that it poured out was, and disburſt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An incorruptible inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THe Ponderous weight of that felicity,</l>
                     <l>And bleſſedneſs which is poſſeſſed by</l>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:63305:28"/>
                     <l>The ſaints, who there the royal ſcepter ſway,</l>
                     <l>Shall ne're be ſubject to the leaſt decay.</l>
                     <l>Much leſs ſhall their illuſtrious condition</l>
                     <l>Obnoxious be to any abolition.</l>
                     <l>But their unſpeakable beatitude</l>
                     <l>All diminution wholly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hall exclude:</l>
                     <l>And alwayes be as freſh and full as at</l>
                     <l>The firſt it was, their glorified eſtate</l>
                     <l>Shall ne're decline, but without ſpot or ſtain</l>
                     <l>Through all eternity entire remain.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An Exceeding, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal weight of Glory.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>HEaven <hi>an exceeding and eternal weight</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of Glory</hi> ſtiled is, its pompe and ſtate,</l>
                     <l>Crowns, kingdoms, jewels, and moſt orient</l>
                     <l>Pearls can to us but weakly repreſent,</l>
                     <l>And darkly ſhadow out; it is (ſaith one)</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A</hi> phraſe ſuperlative, and ſuch as none</l>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:63305:28"/>
                     <l>Of all the Heathen in their Or atory</l>
                     <l>Could ever reach unto, becauſe heavens glory</l>
                     <l>Is too tranſcendent, too ſublime and high,</l>
                     <l>E're to be ken'd by Natures pur-blind eye.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:63305:29"/>
               <head>THE SAINTS SHALL BE WITH CHRIST IN HEAVEN.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe Doctor of the Gentiles grand deſire</l>
                  <l>To be diſſolved was, he did aſpire</l>
                  <l>To the encircling armes of Chriſt, which he</l>
                  <l>Deemed the center of felicitie;</l>
                  <l>A Priviledge of the firſt magnitude,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi> bleſſing that all bleſſings did include.</l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:63305:29"/>
                  <l>Surely we can no loſers be by being</l>
                  <l>With Chriſt who is almighty and all-ſeeing,</l>
                  <l>While we 're engarriſon'd in ſlime, too much</l>
                  <l>Of the wild olive ſtill remains in ſuch</l>
                  <l>As are indeed converted, but when death</l>
                  <l>Dams up the paſſage of our fleeting breath,</l>
                  <l>As young and tender <hi>Scions,</hi> then ſhall we</l>
                  <l>Into a better ſtock engrafted be:</l>
                  <l>We then ſhall be with Chriſt, whoſe company</l>
                  <l>Our hearts will raviſh to eternity.</l>
                  <l>A perfect ſtate more glorious is by far</l>
                  <l>Than an imperfect; here our graces are</l>
                  <l>Our richeſt jewels, but their luſtre they</l>
                  <l>Don't in this life unto the full diſplay:</l>
                  <l>They'r like the Moon, which when it ſhines moſt bright,</l>
                  <l>Hath a dark ſpot moſt obvious to our ſight;</l>
                  <l>Our pretious Faith (a jewel in Gods eye)</l>
                  <l>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> blended is with incredulity,</l>
                  <l>And our humility with ſo much pride</l>
                  <l>Is ſtain'd, that it can hardly be deſcri'd;</l>
                  <l>Our graces flame (alas) is not ſo pure,</l>
                  <l>But that ſome ſmoak doth often it obſcure;</l>
                  <l>Our Vertues here are in their infancy,</l>
                  <l>And can't arrive at full maturity,</l>
                  <l>Till on the top of <hi>Jacobs</hi> Ladder we</l>
                  <l>Are mounted, and do Chriſt in heaven ſee:</l>
                  <l>To be with Chriſt is held in ſacred ſtory</l>
                  <l>To be the higheſt link i'th chain of glory.</l>
                  <l>What is't the pious ſoul eſteems moſt meet</l>
                  <l>For him to covet? is it not the ſweet</l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:63305:30"/>
                  <l>Preſence of Chriſt? For nought on earth he cares</l>
                  <l>But what the image of his Saviour bears.</l>
                  <l>He loves religious duties, but whence is't?</l>
                  <l>Becauſe they manuductions are to Chriſt:</l>
                  <l>He prayes and praiſeth prayers excellence,</l>
                  <l>Cauſe ſouls with Chriſt have private conference:</l>
                  <l>He hears the Word, and ſtrives it to obey,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe to Chriſt it ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lketh out the way.</l>
                  <l>Chriſt on the ſpirits wings to us doth flie,</l>
                  <l>VVe plume'd with Faith to him again do hie.</l>
                  <l>If in an O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d'nance Chriſt be not, inſteed</l>
                  <l>Of meat we on an empty diſh do feed.</l>
                  <l>Chriſt's all a Chriſtian can deſire, and more.</l>
                  <l>The ſev'ral graces which i'th ſaints of yore</l>
                  <l>A pleaſing luſter yielded though but dim,</l>
                  <l>Are all at once conſpicuous in him.</l>
                  <l>VVho ſo by Fuith moſt ſublimated is,</l>
                  <l>He neither hath a head-piece to deviſe,</l>
                  <l>Nor heart to cover all that's to be found</l>
                  <l>In Chriſt, but when we on the holy ground</l>
                  <l>Of heaven tread, the great <hi>Jehovah</hi> will</l>
                  <l>Enlarge our narrow Veſſels, and them fill</l>
                  <l>Up to the very brim, as once with VVine</l>
                  <l>Chriſt did the water-pots by's power Divine.</l>
                  <l>The ſight of Chriſt unto a ſaint, that is</l>
                  <l>Tranſlated and enammelled with bliſs,</l>
                  <l>A more delightful object will appear</l>
                  <l>Than e're his eyes beheld: VVhen he was here</l>
                  <l>On earth, the light of his Divinitie</l>
                  <l>In the dark-la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thorn did obſcured lie</l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:63305:30"/>
                  <l>Of his humanity, yet even then</l>
                  <l>The ſaints in him did ſo much beauty ken,</l>
                  <l>Through Faiths proſpective-glaſs, as did delight</l>
                  <l>Their hearts, and raviſh their amazed ſight.</l>
                  <l>But Oh! what glittering beams of matchleſs worth,</l>
                  <l>And peerleſs excellence ſhall ſparkle forth</l>
                  <l>From Chriſt, when ſaints ſhall ſee him as he is,</l>
                  <l>Shining in glory in the ſphear of bliſs.</l>
                  <l>O what a bleſſed ſight will't be to ſee,</l>
                  <l>Chriſt clad i'th' Robes of our humanity!</l>
                  <l>And in that humane nature placed higher</l>
                  <l>In dignity, than the melodious Quire</l>
                  <l>Of glorious Angels, who to heavens King,</l>
                  <l>Do everlaſting <hi>Halelujahs</hi> ſing.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cherubs</hi> and <hi>Seraphims</hi> there are; But do</l>
                  <l>The ſaints believe that theſe make heaven? No;</l>
                  <l>I'th' ring of glory, Chriſt's the rareſt Gem;</l>
                  <l>The richeſt Pearl i'th' heavenly Diadem:</l>
                  <l>Therefore, St. <hi>Paul</hi> deſired not to be</l>
                  <l>In heaven, but with Chriſt, whoſe company</l>
                  <l>The heaven is of heav'ns—</l>
                  <l>Our being with our bleſſed Saviour, ſhall</l>
                  <l>Not only local be, but conjugal;</l>
                  <l>Our eyes ſhall ſo behold him, as that we</l>
                  <l>Shall be one with him to eternity:</l>
                  <l>What neerer is than Union? or what's ſweeter?</l>
                  <l>It is the ſpring of joy, and makes the creature</l>
                  <l>Happy beyond conceit: by vertue we</l>
                  <l>Of that bleſt Union, ſhall partakers be</l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:63305:31"/>
                  <l>Of thoſe tranſcendent beauties, wherewithal</l>
                  <l>Chriſt's humane nature is, and ever ſhall</l>
                  <l>Beſpangled be; Chriſt with the glory which</l>
                  <l>His Father gave him, will his ſaints enrich:</l>
                  <l>They with his beams ſhall ſhine, he doth array</l>
                  <l>Them with his graces, whilſt they'r in the way;</l>
                  <l>But when they to their journeys end are come,</l>
                  <l>He, them with Robes of Glory welcomes home.</l>
                  <l>How full of luſtre, will the ſaints appear,</l>
                  <l>When they their Saviors richeſt jewels wear!</l>
                  <l>Not only one, they with their husband ſhall</l>
                  <l>Then be, but eke reſemble him withal:</l>
                  <l>In other marriages Brides only do</l>
                  <l>Change their eſtate, but here complexion too:</l>
                  <l>Not that in glory, Chriſt conferreth ought</l>
                  <l>Of his own Eſſence, as <hi>Socinus</hi> taught.</l>
                  <l>Saints ſo much glory as compriz'd may be</l>
                  <l>Within the verge of their humanitie</l>
                  <l>Shall have; but though his image he impart,</l>
                  <l>Yet not his Eſſence. When the Sun doth dart</l>
                  <l>Its beams, and on a glaſs ſhines from its ſphaere,</l>
                  <l>Some print, it of its beauty leaveth there;</l>
                  <l>And 'twixt the Sun-beam and the glaſs, it is</l>
                  <l>No eaſie matter to diſeern; but this</l>
                  <l>Moſt certain is, the glaſs is not the ray,</l>
                  <l>The Sun its likeneſs only doth convey.</l>
               </lg>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:63305:31"/>
                  <head>In Heaven, the Saints ſhall be all KINGS.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THere too too many are, who do aſpire</l>
                     <l>After <hi>Terreſtrial Scepters,</hi> whoſe deſire</l>
                     <l>Is to be mounted on the throne, as though</l>
                     <l>The place where ſaints muſt reign, were here below.</l>
                     <l>We ſurely then, Gods Church on Earth muſt grant</l>
                     <l>To be triumphant, and not militant.</l>
                     <l>But ſee the honour of the ſaints; O they</l>
                     <l>Shall all be Kings at their aſcenſion day:</l>
                     <l>VVe, of their royal robe, and throne of Glory,</l>
                     <l>Read in the Book of Books the ſacred ſtory.</l>
                     <l>The ſaints, that in this world a crown do wear</l>
                     <l>Of thorns, ſhall have a crown of glory there:</l>
                     <l>Yea, ſuch a crown as hath no cares at all</l>
                     <l>VVoven into't; the crown of Kings oft gall</l>
                     <l>Their royal heads, they by experience find</l>
                     <l>Them both with care and ſorrow to be lin'd.</l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:63305:32"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cyrus,</hi> the <hi>Perſian</hi> King, was wont to ſay,</l>
                     <l>Did men but know the cares, which he each day</l>
                     <l>Under a crown, imperial, did ſuſtain;</l>
                     <l>To take it up no doubt they would diſdain.</l>
                     <l>But lo the crowns of ſaints, in glory ſhal</l>
                     <l>No mixture know, or miſery at all:</l>
                     <l>They neither are with care of keeping blent,</l>
                     <l>Or fear of loſing, but yield all content.</l>
                     <l>O let us then with patience undergo</l>
                     <l>Our momentary troubles here below:</l>
                     <l>Let not our light afflictions preſs us down,</l>
                     <l>VVho bear the croſs, ſhall alſo were the crown.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:63305:32"/>
                  <head>In Heaven the Saints ſhall be filled with JOY.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THe <hi>joy of Saints</hi> is by their Union bred</l>
                     <l>VVith Chriſt; being fully joyn'd to their Head,</l>
                     <l>Their <hi>joyes</hi> ſhall then be perfect, and for ay</l>
                     <l>God from their eyes ſhall wipe all tears away</l>
                     <l>With that ſoft ſpung, which Chriſt their truſty friend</l>
                     <l>Provided hath before hand for that end.</l>
                     <l>The ſpouſe on Earth in ſable doth appear,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe ſhe abſent is from her moſt dear</l>
                     <l>And loving husband; but in heaven ſhe</l>
                     <l>Of all her mourning weeds ſhall ſtripped be:</l>
                     <l>Her bloody Robes Chriſt then will take away,</l>
                     <l>And all in white will her forthwith array.</l>
                     <l>Hell's call'd a place of weeping, they that here,</l>
                     <l>For all their ſins would never ſhed a tear,</l>
                     <l>Shall weep enough, when they tormented ly</l>
                     <l>I' th' ſcorching flames of endleſs miſery.</l>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:63305:33"/>
                     <l>But when the ſaints have gain'd the heav'nly crown,</l>
                     <l>Chriſt from the willows will their harps take down.</l>
                     <l>He, for his trumpeters and heraulds there</l>
                     <l>VVill call, who at his beck do all appear.</l>
                     <l>The glorious Angels, that caeleſtial Quire,</l>
                     <l>VVith one conſent, do mutually conſpire,</l>
                     <l>To warble forth the anthemes of divine</l>
                     <l>Praiſe, and with them the ſaints ſhall all combine,</l>
                     <l>And ſhall with wondrous skill and heavenly art</l>
                     <l>In that bleſt conſort, ſweetly ſing their part.</l>
                     <l>If when we are i'th'arms of Chriſt, it were</l>
                     <l>Poſſible for a ſaint to ſhed a tear,</l>
                     <l>It would, without all paradventure, be</l>
                     <l>A tear of joy. Chriſt to eternitie</l>
                     <l>VVith beams of love, upon his ſpouſe will ſhine,</l>
                     <l>And all her water there turn into wine.</l>
                     <l>One ſmile from Chriſt, will make her quite forget</l>
                     <l>Her former grievances, and ſtrait-way ſet</l>
                     <l>Her on the pinacle of joy, where ſhe</l>
                     <l>From all afflictions ever ſhall be free.</l>
                     <l>Sorrow's a cloud, that's gather'd in the heart,</l>
                     <l>Upon the apprehenſion of ſome ſmart:</l>
                     <l>And weeping, which the off-ſpring is of pain,</l>
                     <l>A cloud of grief is dropping into rain.</l>
                     <l>But Chriſt the ſun of Righteouſneſs, ſhall ſhine</l>
                     <l>So brightly in the heavenly <hi>Palaeſtine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That there no interpoſing clouds ſhall be;</l>
                     <l>No ſorrow mix'd with our felicitie.</l>
                     <l>In heaven there's no Devil to entice,</l>
                     <l>Nothing to breed, or to engender vice.</l>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:63305:33"/>
                     <l>Saints in the boſome there of peace ſhall reſt,</l>
                     <l>No enemy there ſhall be to moleſt.</l>
                     <l>Though <hi>Iſr'el</hi> had ſubdued <hi>Canaan,</hi> yet</l>
                     <l>Of all the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> they could not get</l>
                     <l>The maſtery, or wholly them expel;</l>
                     <l>But they, amongſt them in that Land would dwell.</l>
                     <l>But when we with the Father are of Lights,</l>
                     <l>VVe ſhall no more be vex'd with <hi>Canaanites.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>God with a flaming ſword, world without end,</l>
                     <l>The heavenly paradiſe ſhall ſtill defend.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:63305:34"/>
                  <head>The Saints in Heaven ſhall have perfect Rest.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A Pilgrime <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, i'th' vale of miſerie,</l>
                     <l>May to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſilver well reſembled be,</l>
                     <l>Which hath a principle of motion in it,</l>
                     <l>But not of <hi>Reſt:</hi> he almoſt every minute</l>
                     <l>Is like the Ball upon the Racket, or</l>
                     <l>The ſhip upon the waves that ſwell and rore.</l>
                     <l>So long as ſin our nature doth deface,</l>
                     <l>And a co-habitant remains with grace,</l>
                     <l>While Saints do feed on ſuch unwholſome diet,</l>
                     <l>They ſubject are to motion and diſquiet.</l>
                     <l>There is no <hi>reſt</hi> (ſaith holy <hi>David</hi>) in</l>
                     <l>My bones at all, by reaſon of my ſin:</l>
                     <l>Here ſaints are in a conſtant fluctuation,</l>
                     <l>And of their ſorrows have no relaxation:</l>
                     <l>They'r like the tyde that flows ſometime, and than</l>
                     <l>After a while doth ebb as faſt again.</l>
                     <l>No reſt on earth is to be had, 'cauſe we,</l>
                     <l>While here below, out of our center be.</l>
                     <l>The Dove no reſt after a tedious flight</l>
                     <l>Could find, till on the Ark ſhe did alight.</l>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:63305:34"/>
                     <l>But when the ſaints in heaven do arive,</l>
                     <l>An everlaſting reſt ſhall them revive.</l>
                     <l>The winds of perſecution often blow</l>
                     <l>Upon this ſpiritual corn, whilſt it doth grow</l>
                     <l>Here in the field, and each one paſſing by</l>
                     <l>Will ſtill be plucking moſt inhumanely</l>
                     <l>Theſe ſacred ears of corn; but when this crop</l>
                     <l>Is in the heavenly Grainery laid up,</l>
                     <l>It from the injury of wind and weather</l>
                     <l>Shall then preſerved be for altogether:</l>
                     <l>It with impetuous ſtorms no more oppreſt</l>
                     <l>Shall be at all, but ever be at reſt.</l>
                     <l>Not that in heaven there's no principle</l>
                     <l>Of motion, ſpirits neither can nor will</l>
                     <l>Be idle there, but ſuch a motion 'tis</l>
                     <l>As without laſſitude and labour is.</l>
                     <l>No wearineſs the ſaints ſhall there infeſt,</l>
                     <l>Their work's their caſe, their motion is their reſt:</l>
                     <l>They labour here for reſt, but there they ſhall</l>
                     <l>Reſt from their labours, and be freed from thrall.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:63305:35"/>
                  <head>The Saints in Heaven ſhall have full Security.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>'TIs poſſible a ſaint ſome minutes may</l>
                     <l>Of reſt have here, but they ſoon paſs away:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Security</hi>'s a flower that doth not grow,</l>
                     <l>In Natures Garden, whilſt we're here below,</l>
                     <l>Sudden eclipſes in our hemiſphear</l>
                     <l>To over-cloud our comforts oft appear.</l>
                     <l>We here in danger are of loſing what</l>
                     <l>Our heav'n-bleſt induſtry hath fairly got.</l>
                     <l>He that upon the pinnacle is plac't</l>
                     <l>Of honour, doubts his honour will not laſt:</l>
                     <l>He that abounds in worldly wealth ſtill fears</l>
                     <l>A devaſtation by the plunderers:</l>
                     <l>Nay a Believer, though his riches be</l>
                     <l>Moſt permanent and durable, yet he</l>
                     <l>Still pendulous and full of ſcruples is</l>
                     <l>'Bout his condition, leſt of heaven he miſs:</l>
                     <l>Sometimes he queſtions, and would gladly know,</l>
                     <l>Whether in the ſtate of grace he be or no?</l>
                     <l>When Satan hath o're-reach'd him in ſome plot,</l>
                     <l>Do I believe (ſaith he) or do I not?</l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:63305:35"/>
                     <l>Something I have that ſhines, but is not it</l>
                     <l>A chain of pearl that's only counterfeit?</l>
                     <l>My Faith's preſumption and my love what is't</l>
                     <l>But love of ſelf, and no true love to Chriſt.</l>
                     <l>Yea, when the holy Spirit hath me taught</l>
                     <l>And in my ſoul ſome ſound perſwaſion wrought</l>
                     <l>I ſoon am ſhaken like a ſhip that lies</l>
                     <l>At anchor, when the ſwaggering billows riſe.</l>
                     <l>Thus theſe diſtracting fears oft make him ſtart,</l>
                     <l>And ſad impreſſions leave upon his heart</l>
                     <l>Yea, when a chriſtian knows himſelf to be</l>
                     <l>I'the ſtate of Grace, yet then he fears leſt he</l>
                     <l>Into ſome ſcandalous offence ſhould fall,</l>
                     <l>And ſo Gods ſpirit grieve, and deeply gall</l>
                     <l>His own awakened conſcience, and the heart</l>
                     <l>Of Gods dear children pierce through with this dart,</l>
                     <l>Leſt he thereby ſhould ſinners harden, and</l>
                     <l>Make Babes in Grace affrighted at him ſtand;</l>
                     <l>Yea, which is worſt of all, leſt God his ſpark</l>
                     <l>Extinguiſh ſhould, and leave him in the dark:</l>
                     <l>Theſe fears out of a gracious heart are ſtill</l>
                     <l>Ariſing like black vapours, and do fill</l>
                     <l>The ſouls of ſaints with ſorrow, but when they</l>
                     <l>Releaſed are out of their houſe of clay,</l>
                     <l>And in th' embraces of their Saviour lye,</l>
                     <l>Their hearts ſhall then have full ſecurity;</l>
                     <l>When they with Chriſt in glory ſhall appear,</l>
                     <l>They ſhall be rid of dangers and of fear.</l>
                     <l>A Chriſtian in this life may likened be</l>
                     <l>Unto a man upon the ſummitie.</l>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:63305:36"/>
                     <l>Of ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>all Maſte, ſometime the pirates (I</l>
                     <l>Mean perecutors) at his ſhip let fly;</l>
                     <l>And though the paſſenger can't be annoy'd,</l>
                     <l>To wit, the ſoul, yet oft the ſhip's deſtroy'd.</l>
                     <l>Sometimes the winds of ſtrong temptation blow,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe northern winds, and the poor chriſtian now</l>
                     <l>Gods favour queſtions much, and gladly would</l>
                     <l>Know if his name were in Gods Book enrould.</l>
                     <l>And though in Chriſt having an intereſt,</l>
                     <l>There is no danger, yet his heart can't reſt.</l>
                     <l>But when he is with Chriſt off from the maſt,</l>
                     <l>And planted on that rock, all peril's paſt:</l>
                     <l>Then you ſhall hear him ſay, Now I am ſure</l>
                     <l>I've ſhot the Gulf, my ſoul is now <hi>ſecure:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I'm paſt from death to life, no <hi>Sirens</hi> charms</l>
                     <l>Henceforth can pluck me from my Saviors arms.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:63305:36"/>
                  <head>In Heaven there ſhall be a Vindication of Names.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THough Saints a conſcience here void of offence</l>
                     <l>Towards God &amp; man have, yet their innocence</l>
                     <l>By poyſoned arrows of malitious words</l>
                     <l>Oft wounded is, which ſharper are than ſwords.</l>
                     <l>The Devil that old ſerpent ſticks not to</l>
                     <l>Spit out his venome at the godly through</l>
                     <l>The mouths of wicked men, if he can't ſmite</l>
                     <l>Their conſciences with his keen darts, and fright</l>
                     <l>Their ſouls into diſpair, he then will put</l>
                     <l>A dead flie in their <hi>names,</hi> which oft doth cut</l>
                     <l>Them to the very heart, the ſaints we ſee</l>
                     <l>Unto the world oft times decipher'd be</l>
                     <l>In a ſad manner; who can e're expreſs</l>
                     <l>How ſtrangely ſaints look in the Devils dreſs?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Job</hi> to the world was repreſented by</l>
                     <l>His Friends as one ſtain'd with hypocriſie:</l>
                     <l>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was ſtiled a ſeditious man,</l>
                     <l>When he to publiſh heavenly truths began.</l>
                     <l>The marks of Chriſt he in his body did</l>
                     <l>Not only bear, but in his <hi>name</hi> beſide.</l>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:63305:37"/>
                     <l>Yea, Chriſt himſelf, who bleſſed is for ever</l>
                     <l>Was called of the people a deceiver:</l>
                     <l>And ſtill the Devils inſtruments aſſay</l>
                     <l>The ſaints in ugly colours to pourtray.</l>
                     <l>A hainous ſin, no doubt, 'tis to defame</l>
                     <l>A chriſtian by beſpattering his good name,</l>
                     <l>It is no leſs than murther, rather he</l>
                     <l>Would loſe his life, than's credit ſoyl'd ſhould be.</l>
                     <l>Who ſo his neighbor wounds in's reputation</l>
                     <l>For it can never make him reparation.</l>
                     <l>Flaws in mens credit are like blots in white</l>
                     <l>Paper, which one can hardly fetch out quite.</l>
                     <l>Or if the wound it ſelf ſhould cured be,</l>
                     <l>Some skar to their perpetual obloquie</l>
                     <l>Would ſtill remain; in fine, they do defame</l>
                     <l>The God of ſaints, who blaſt the ſaints good name.</l>
                     <l>Believers have Gods picture on their hearts,</l>
                     <l>And he that caſteth his malitious darts</l>
                     <l>Againſt it, or prophanely ſpits upon't,</l>
                     <l>Offers to God himſelf no ſmall affront:</l>
                     <l>Well, either God the innocence will clear</l>
                     <l>Of his Elect, while they do ſojourn here.</l>
                     <l>when graceleſs-men them with their tongus do ſmite</l>
                     <l>Their righteouſneſs hee'l bring forth as the light,</l>
                     <l>Or elſe without all peradventure at</l>
                     <l>The day of Doom their names he'l vindicate,</l>
                     <l>Though troublers now of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſtiled they be,</l>
                     <l>The day ſhall come when their integritie</l>
                     <l>By him ſhall be proclaim'd, who only knows</l>
                     <l>The hearts of men, and can their thoughts diſcloſe.</l>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:63305:37"/>
                     <l>The duſt that here upon their reputation</l>
                     <l>Was thrown by men of evil converſation</l>
                     <l>Shall then be wiped off, and they no more</l>
                     <l>Shall loaded be with ſcandals as before.</l>
                     <l>The credits then of thoſe ſhall be redeem'd,</l>
                     <l>Of whom the world ſo baſely here eſteem'd.</l>
                     <l>For names <hi>Jehovah</hi> (who is great and good)</l>
                     <l>Shall inquiſition make as well as blood;</l>
                     <l>And then the ſaints ſhall ſuch a luſter gain,</l>
                     <l>As no polluted breath can ever ſtain.</l>
                     <l>Then God himſelf the ſtone of obloquie</l>
                     <l>Which here below on their good names did lye,</l>
                     <l>Eſtſoons ſhall roul away and they out from</l>
                     <l>Among the pots immediately ſhal come,</l>
                     <l>Where they were black'd and ſulled, and ſhal be</l>
                     <l>No more traduced to eternity.</l>
                     <l>They then muſt needs appear without a blur,</l>
                     <l>When God himſelf is their compurgator.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:63305:38"/>
                  <head>The Graces of the Saints ſhall be perfect in heaven.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>HEre <hi>Grace</hi> to ſilver may reſembled be,</l>
                     <l>Which hath ſome droſs blent with its purity;</l>
                     <l>But when 'tis coined in the heavenly mint,</l>
                     <l>No mixture of corruption ſhall be in't.</l>
                     <l>When we're advanc'd to the caeleſtial throne,</l>
                     <l>Grace ſhall be flowr'd into perfection:</l>
                     <l>It then moſt certainly refin'd ſhall be</l>
                     <l>Into the higheſt power and purity.</l>
                     <l>This contemplation ſhould unto a ſaint</l>
                     <l>Be very ſweet, our love hath here, I grant,</l>
                     <l>Its winter in our breaſts, but it ſhall be</l>
                     <l>As fire <hi>ad octo</hi> in eternitie.</l>
                     <l>No ſmoak of imperfection ſhall obſcure</l>
                     <l>That radiant flame, or render it impure.</l>
                     <l>Our <hi>graces</hi> in ſuch orient colours there</l>
                     <l>As never can be ſoyled ſhall appear.</l>
                     <l>There <hi>grace</hi> ſhall want no meaſure no degree,</l>
                     <l>But to eternity ſhall perfect be.</l>
                     <l>It may be here compared to a ſtar</l>
                     <l>Impriſon'd in a cloud, but when we are</l>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:63305:38"/>
                     <l>Once fixed in the firmament one high,</l>
                     <l>It like the ſun in a moſt glorious skye</l>
                     <l>Shall then appear, and there a regal crown</l>
                     <l>Of rare and matchleſs beauty ſhall put on.</l>
                     <l>In fine, 'tis manifeſt in ſacred ſtory,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>grace</hi> ſhall then be ſwallow'd up in glory.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:63305:39"/>
               <head>THE BEAUTY AND BLESSEDNESS OF <hi>Glorified Bodies.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHile we're on Earth, our earthly tabernacle</l>
                  <l>Is of infirmities the receptacle,</l>
                  <l>Phyſicians find with all their art and skill</l>
                  <l>Enough to do to piece't up for a while.</l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:63305:39"/>
                  <l>Our houſe of clay like to a picture is,</l>
                  <l>That's out of frame, or like an edifice</l>
                  <l>That wants repair; how ſoon each ſudden blaſt</l>
                  <l>Of ſickneſs doth its ſtrength and beauty waſt?</l>
                  <l>How often is the heaven-born ſpirit pent</l>
                  <l>Up in a moſt deformed tenement?</l>
                  <l>To rotten wood the body may indeed</l>
                  <l>Be likened, where like worms diſeaſes breed:</l>
                  <l>But yet this piece of clay beſpangled ſhall</l>
                  <l>With glory be above in heavens <hi>VVhitehall.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No Feaver there or Pluriſie ſhall be,</l>
                  <l>No wound, diſtemper, or deformity</l>
                  <l>But all the iſſues of infirmity,</l>
                  <l>That here beſet the holieſt ſaints ſhall dry</l>
                  <l>Up in illuſtrious ſplendour, there for aye</l>
                  <l>With greater beauty God ſhall them array</l>
                  <l>Then that of <hi>Phoebus,</hi> when it ſhines moſt bright,</l>
                  <l>And blaz'ned is in its meridian light:</l>
                  <l>There <hi>Leah</hi> ſhan't complain of her blear eyes,</l>
                  <l>Nor ag'd <hi>Barzilla</hi> of infirmities.</l>
                  <l>Whither the bodies glory doth rebound</l>
                  <l>From the ſouls bleſſedneſs and ſo redound</l>
                  <l>By a continued conſtant influence</l>
                  <l>Upon the body, with much diligence</l>
                  <l>I ſhall not here enquire, or whether by</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jchovahs</hi> powerful hand originally</l>
                  <l>In the reformed body 'tis implanted,</l>
                  <l>This in the general is on all ſides granted,</l>
                  <l>That in the morning of the reſurrection</l>
                  <l>It ſhall be raiſed up in great perfection:</l>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:63305:40"/>
                  <l>And like the glorious Body of our dear</l>
                  <l>Saviour in heavenly ſplendor ſhall appear:</l>
                  <l>Which is a happineſs moſt excellent,</l>
                  <l>Superlative and ſupereminent.</l>
               </lg>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Glorified BODYES immortal.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>DEath is the bitter and accurſed fruit</l>
                     <l>Of ſin, a worm ſtill feeding at the root</l>
                     <l>Of our decaying Gourds, but when we die,</l>
                     <l>Our mortal puts on immort alitie.</l>
                     <l>As 'twas with <hi>Adam</hi> in his innocence,</l>
                     <l>Had not ſin ſtript him of his excellence,</l>
                     <l>Such harmony between each quality</l>
                     <l>There of his Body was, that probably</l>
                     <l>Of life he never ſhould have been bereaven,</l>
                     <l>But have tranſlated been to th'higheſt heaven,</l>
                     <l>Indeed by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> it is averr'd,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Adam</hi> dy'd had, though he ne're had err'd.</l>
                     <l>But there's no ground for this aſſertion in</l>
                     <l>The ſacred ſcripture to be found, there ſin</l>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:63305:40"/>
                     <l>Is made the formal cauſe of death, however,</l>
                     <l>Death our bodies glorified ſhall never</l>
                     <l>Dominion have, but they by heavens decree</l>
                     <l>Are made as long liv'd as eternity.</l>
                     <l>That God, who <hi>Manna</hi> made ſome ages paſt</l>
                     <l>Hundreds of years'th' golden pot to laſt,</l>
                     <l>Shall ſo conſolidate the body by</l>
                     <l>His ſoveraign power, that it ſhall never die,</l>
                     <l>But with impoſſibility of ever</l>
                     <l>Periſhing ſhall in blisful ſtate perſevere.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:63305:41"/>
                  <head>Heavenly Bodies impaſsible</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>SOul grinding ſores <hi>Jobs</hi> Body ſoft and tender</l>
                     <l>Invaded, and therein did worms engender:</l>
                     <l>And every worm was actuated by</l>
                     <l>A Devil to augment his miſery,</l>
                     <l>(As <hi>Origen</hi> aſſerts) converted <hi>Paul,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who was ſometime before his funeral</l>
                     <l>Bath'd in the chryſtal ſtreams of heavenly bliſs,</l>
                     <l>Did in his body bear the marks of his</l>
                     <l>Dear Lord and Saviour: but our bodies when</l>
                     <l>They are poſſeſſed of the magazen</l>
                     <l>Of bleſſedneſs, impaſſible ſhal be</l>
                     <l>From agonizing torments wholly free,</l>
                     <l>That ſuch a paſſion bodies glorifi'd</l>
                     <l>Have, as delightful is, can't be deny'd,</l>
                     <l>Since they of joy are capable, but this</l>
                     <l>Is certain, when they in the lap of bliſs</l>
                     <l>Once dandled are, to violence they ſhal</l>
                     <l>Ne're be expos'd, or miſery at all.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:63305:41"/>
                  <head>Heavenly Bodies Agile.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THe bodies of the ſaints tereſtrial</l>
                     <l>Are heavy in their motion, but they ſhal</l>
                     <l>Be with incredible agility</l>
                     <l>Endow'd, when they above the blew-flowr'd sky</l>
                     <l>Tranſlated are into the throne of bliſs,</l>
                     <l>Which for triumphant ſaints prepared is.</l>
                     <l>A lump of Lead which to the bottom ſtil</l>
                     <l>Sinks, being wyre-drawn by the workmans skil</l>
                     <l>Into the form and faſhion of a Boat,</l>
                     <l>(Saith <hi>Auſten</hi>) wil upon the waters float:</l>
                     <l>And ſhal not God give that ability</l>
                     <l>Unto the body of a ſaint, when by</l>
                     <l>His ſovereign power 'tis rais'd up from the dead,</l>
                     <l>Which the artificer gives to the Lead:</l>
                     <l>The ſoul is in its operations by</l>
                     <l>The bodies lumpiſh ponderoſity</l>
                     <l>Obſtructed here, when e're it doth aſſay</l>
                     <l>Unto the heavenly throne to make its way,</l>
                     <l>Or Would aſpire to the caeleſtial crown,</l>
                     <l>That like a Leaden-plummet puls at down.</l>
                     <l>But when the grave from out its pregnant womb</l>
                     <l>Shal caſt its treaſure, at the day of doom,</l>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:63305:42"/>
                     <l>When ſaints out of their beds of earth ſhal riſe,</l>
                     <l>And be refin'd, it ſhal be otherwiſe:</l>
                     <l>Elementary gravity ſhal no</l>
                     <l>Impeding obſtacle ere be unto</l>
                     <l>Their bodies then, but ſwift and facile they</l>
                     <l>Shal in their motion be, and that for ay.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:63305:42"/>
                  <head>Heavenly BODYES Amiable</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THe Body when to Heaven it takes its flight</l>
                     <l>Shal be like iron filed and made bright,</l>
                     <l>It ſhal coruſcant be, and with divine</l>
                     <l>Luſter in the celeſtial Orbe ſhal ſhine.</l>
                     <l>Like to the ſun in ſplendor it ſhal be,</l>
                     <l>Nay ſeven times brighter in its claritie:</l>
                     <l>The Body of a ſaint impure before</l>
                     <l>And droſsy, like the Gold when in the ore,</l>
                     <l>Shal gliſter, when reform'd and glorifi'd,</l>
                     <l>Like burniſht Gold i'th' furnace often try'd.</l>
                     <l>It ſo tranſparent then and clear no doubt</l>
                     <l>Shal be, as that the ſoul ſhal ſally out</l>
                     <l>At every part, and through the bodies as</l>
                     <l>The VVine ſhal ſparkle through a Venice-glaſs.</l>
                     <l>Such glorious brightneſs and reſplendency</l>
                     <l>The body ſteeped in felicity</l>
                     <l>Innoble ſhal, that ſhould we it compare</l>
                     <l>VVith <hi>Sols</hi> moſt radiant beams that gild the air,</l>
                     <l>VVe to th'expreſſion of the excellence</l>
                     <l>Of its illuſtrious pre-eminence</l>
                     <l>Shal nothing ſay at all —.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:63305:43"/>
                  <head>The beauty and bleſſedneſs of Glorified Souls.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>IT would an endleſs labour be no doubt,</l>
                     <l>If I ſhould undertake to ſhadow out</l>
                     <l>The ſeveral glories of each faculty</l>
                     <l>Of the refined ſoul, (undoubtedly)</l>
                     <l>All humane rhetorick and angelical</l>
                     <l>Too narrow is e're to expreſs them al</l>
                     <l>Unto the life, my purpoſe only is</l>
                     <l>A taſte to give you of its perfect bliſs:</l>
                     <l>Yet from thoſe cluſters which I here preſent,</l>
                     <l>A ſaint may reap much ſweetneſs and content.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:63305:43"/>
                  <head>The Saints Knowledge per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in Heaven.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THe intellectual part enlarg'd ſhal be</l>
                     <l>With knowledge ith' ſuperlative degree,</l>
                     <l>It all things there cognoſcible ſhal know,</l>
                     <l>That from its eye were vailed here below:</l>
                     <l>Whatever knowledge comes within the ſphear</l>
                     <l>Of finite underſtandings it ſhal there</l>
                     <l>Perfectly comprehend, no myſtery</l>
                     <l>Shal ſcape the ken of its enlightened eye.</l>
                     <l>Knowledge of nature, arts, and things created</l>
                     <l>Delightful is, and highly eſtimated.</l>
                     <l>Some Heathens were with Philoſophical</l>
                     <l>Wiſdom, and beams of intellectual</l>
                     <l>Light ſo enamour'd, that they did contemne</l>
                     <l>The world as nothing to that peerleſs Gem.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aeneas Silvius</hi> long ago did ſay</l>
                     <l>Unto a Doctor once of <hi>Auſtria,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That if the face of humane Learning could</l>
                     <l>Be ſeen by mortal eyes, it (doubtleſs) would</l>
                     <l>Appear more beautiful and brighter far,</l>
                     <l>Than doth the morning or the evening ſtar.</l>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:63305:44"/>
                     <l>In other pleaſures a ſatiety</l>
                     <l>There is, when they are uſed, by and by</l>
                     <l>Their verdure doth depart, which argues that</l>
                     <l>It is the Novelty doth recreate,</l>
                     <l>And not the Quality, and that they be</l>
                     <l>Pleaſures in thought, not in realitie.</l>
                     <l>Ambitious Princes are not alwayes jolly,</l>
                     <l>But are ſometimes o're-whelm'd with melancholy,</l>
                     <l>And men o're-charged with voluptuouſneſs</l>
                     <l>Oft ſheath their bodies in a Friars dreſs.</l>
                     <l>But there's of Knowledge no ſatiety,</l>
                     <l>The more we drink of this the more we dry:</l>
                     <l>Here <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> and <hi>appetite</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Do meet, with interchangeable delight,</l>
                     <l>Which plainly proves that it is really</l>
                     <l>Good, without accident of fallacy.</l>
                     <l>Now this <hi>inferiour knowledge</hi> to the height</l>
                     <l>Shal there be rais'd by him who dwels in <hi>light,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And ſo compleated be as that the leaſt</l>
                     <l>And loweſt ſaint of heaven once poſſeſt</l>
                     <l>The cauſes of <hi>all natural things</hi> far more</l>
                     <l>Exactly comprehend ſhal than before,</l>
                     <l>And have a clearer ſight of the concluſions</l>
                     <l>Of art, through th' opticks of divine infuſions,</l>
                     <l>Then ere could be attained by the eye</l>
                     <l>Of Nature, Reaſon, or Philoſophy.</l>
                     <l>In every kind of <hi>humane learning</hi> there</l>
                     <l>Some ſtrange <hi>aenigma's</hi> dayly do appear,</l>
                     <l>Which exerciſed have from time to time</l>
                     <l>The braveſt wits, but (ah) ſo dark, ſo dimme</l>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:63305:44"/>
                     <l>By nature, is each intellectual eye,</l>
                     <l>That they thoſe Gordian knots could ne're unty;</l>
                     <l>Whether the rowling Orbes by angels are</l>
                     <l>Mov'd, or internal forms, who can declare?</l>
                     <l>Whether in man three ſouls diſtinct there be,</l>
                     <l>Or one in ſubſtance only vertually</l>
                     <l>Containing th'other two, too intricate</l>
                     <l>A queſtion is for humane wits to ſtate.</l>
                     <l>The ſouls fair wings do flag here and decay,</l>
                     <l>Some feathers ſick are, and oft drop away.</l>
                     <l>Here one Philoſopher of his head oft makes</l>
                     <l>Doleful complaints, his underſtanding akes,</l>
                     <l>His reaſon's dimm'd, a ſecond ſadly cryes,</l>
                     <l>A third's ſoul trembles with uncertainties:</l>
                     <l>One graſps a cloud of errors, and another</l>
                     <l>Spends in untying ſome hard knot or other</l>
                     <l>Much of his time, one's pleas'd to recreate</l>
                     <l>Himſelf i'th' ſhadow of his own conceit,</l>
                     <l>Another al his netves ſo long doth bend</l>
                     <l>Til they oft ſnap aſunder in the end:</l>
                     <l>You <hi>Socrates</hi> may in the twilight ſee</l>
                     <l>Sadly lamenting the obſcuritie</l>
                     <l>Of his benighted ſtate, and telling you,</l>
                     <l>His Lamp can nought but his own darkneſs ſhew.</l>
                     <l>You may diſcover <hi>Plato</hi> ſitting by</l>
                     <l>The banks of <hi>Lethe</hi> in an agony:</l>
                     <l>And through the limbecks of his moiſtened eyes</l>
                     <l>Diſtilling pearly drops in mournful wiſe,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe he can't by al his induſtry</l>
                     <l>His former Notions cal to memory.</l>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:63305:45"/>
                     <l>Look on the Naturaliſts head and you ſhal ſee</l>
                     <l>It non-pluſt with an occult quality.</l>
                     <l>But when the ſoul aſcendeth up on high,</l>
                     <l>All miſty clouds ſhal be diſpelled by</l>
                     <l>The clear ſun of a knowledge more refin'd,</l>
                     <l>And chas'd out of the region of the mind.</l>
                     <l>So that it then exactly ſhal deſcry</l>
                     <l>The cauſes, natures, riſe and progeny,</l>
                     <l>Together with the ends of al things that</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Jehovahs</hi> powerful word did e're create.</l>
                     <l>It clearly then each Goſpel myſtery</l>
                     <l>Which here ſurpaſt al humane ſcrutiny</l>
                     <l>Shal ſee, and moſt exactly comprehend</l>
                     <l>The darkeſt paſſages that e're were pen'd,</l>
                     <l>Whether <hi>Jobes</hi> wife her plous husband bid</l>
                     <l>Bleſs or Curſe God, and whether <hi>Jephta</hi> did</l>
                     <l>His Daughter ſacrifice to God on high,</l>
                     <l>Or conſecrate her to virginity.</l>
                     <l>Whether <hi>Naaman</hi> a real convert were,</l>
                     <l>Or one in ſemblance only did appear.</l>
                     <l>That ſcripture then each one that runs ſhal read,</l>
                     <l>Why then are they baptized for the dead?</l>
                     <l>When ſaints the heavenly paradiſe inherit,</l>
                     <l>They ſhal be hold with raviſhment of ſpirit</l>
                     <l>Thoſe ſacred myſteries, which here below</l>
                     <l>Some boldly dive into, but cannot know;</l>
                     <l>They then ſhal ſee and ſhal rejoyce to ſee</l>
                     <l>How <hi>three</hi> make <hi>one,</hi> and <hi>one</hi> again makes <hi>three:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>They then ſhal apprehend with admiration</l>
                     <l>The miracles of Chriſt his incarnation,</l>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:63305:45"/>
                     <l>They then the dark and ſecret myſtery</l>
                     <l>Of providence exactly ſhal deſcry.</l>
                     <l>While we in tenements of clay do dwel,</l>
                     <l>What God is doing of we cannot tel:</l>
                     <l>He many times in ſhort-hand writeth, and</l>
                     <l>His characters we cannot underſtand:</l>
                     <l>We ſeeing here but darkly through a glaſs,</l>
                     <l>The footſteps of his providence can't trace:</l>
                     <l>But when we'e veſted in the coſtly dreſs</l>
                     <l>And choice attire of heavens happineſs</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A</hi> reaſon of divine tranſactions we</l>
                     <l>Shal then without al peradventure ſee</l>
                     <l>In every providence we then (no doubt)</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A</hi> wonder or a mercy ſhal ſpy out.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A Limner</hi> at the firſt albeit indu'd</l>
                     <l>With skil enough, yet maketh but a rude</l>
                     <l>Draught in the picture, but when every part</l>
                     <l>And lineament is limm'd out by his art,</l>
                     <l>And in their colours laid, it by and by</l>
                     <l>Appears moſt amiable to the eye.</l>
                     <l>We who in robes of fleſh are cloathed here,</l>
                     <l>Do only ſee a rude draught, as it were</l>
                     <l>Some pieces of myſterious providence</l>
                     <l>Obſcurely ſhadowed out, but when from hence</l>
                     <l>We at the haven of felicity</l>
                     <l>Arrived are, and clearly do deſcry</l>
                     <l>The pourtraiture of providence drawn ous</l>
                     <l>In al its lively colours, it (no doubt)</l>
                     <l>Will be a bleſſed and a glorious ſight,</l>
                     <l>Feeding the ſoul with infinite delight.</l>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:63305:46"/>
                     <l>In fine, when ſaints upon the ſhoar do land</l>
                     <l>Of bleſſedneſs, they then ſhal underſtand</l>
                     <l>The myſtery of hearts, they then ſhal ſee</l>
                     <l>To their content an heart anatomy:</l>
                     <l>For every work with every ſecret thing</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Jehovah</hi> then ſhal into judgement bring.</l>
                     <l>They then the cabinet deſignes ſhal ken,</l>
                     <l>And privy counſels of the hearts of men.</l>
                     <l>The heart is deep, we may it wel compare</l>
                     <l>Unto a river that hath very fair</l>
                     <l>Streams gliding on the top, but when this brook</l>
                     <l>Comes to be drain'd, who ſo doth in it look,</l>
                     <l>Much vermine at the bottom ſhal eſpy,</l>
                     <l>That lay before concealed from the eye:</l>
                     <l>Thus with the heart of man it is, ſome fair</l>
                     <l>Streams running on the top there oft-times are,</l>
                     <l>A civil life, a ſpecious pretence,</l>
                     <l>Of zeal, of purity, and innocence.</l>
                     <l>But when the tryer of the reins ſhal come</l>
                     <l>To drain this river at the day of doom,</l>
                     <l>When God ſhal make a ful diſcovery</l>
                     <l>Of hearts, the crawling vermine by and by</l>
                     <l>Of avarice, and of ambition ſhal</l>
                     <l>Appear, and clearly be diſcern'd of al:</l>
                     <l>All ſecret things ſhal then be brought to light,</l>
                     <l>'Twere worth the dying to behold that ſight.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:63305:46"/>
                  <head>The Saints Love perfected in Heaven.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>LOve</hi> is the jewel, the rich ornament,</l>
                     <l>with which Chriſts Bride is deckt, more excellent</l>
                     <l>'Tis in a ſenſe than Faith, for <hi>love</hi> doth never</l>
                     <l>Ceaſe, but abides for aye, as ſoon as ever</l>
                     <l>The ſaints to heaven come, Faiths orient Gem</l>
                     <l>They ſtraight put off, but not <hi>loves Diadem.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Loves ſparkling beams with their reſplendency</l>
                     <l>Shal gild the ſoul to al eternity.</l>
                     <l>VVhile here below we wallow in the mire,</l>
                     <l>Our love to God is rather a deſire.</l>
                     <l>But when upon the ſpicy Mountain we</l>
                     <l>Of bliſs are lodg'd, and face to face do ſee;</l>
                     <l>VVhen <hi>Hallelujahs</hi> we ſhal with the quire</l>
                     <l>Of angels ſing, the ſmoak then of deſire</l>
                     <l>Into a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ame of Love blown up ſhal be,</l>
                     <l>VVe then ſhal Love God in the higheſt degree.</l>
                     <l>Our love is luke-warme here, and ſometimes frozen,</l>
                     <l>It much afflicts the ſpirits of the choſen,</l>
                     <l>That in the grace of Love they are ſo poor,</l>
                     <l>And that they can their Maker love no more.</l>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:63305:47"/>
                     <l>But there's a time approaching ſhortly whan</l>
                     <l>Their Love ſhal blaze and burn as hot as't can.</l>
                     <l>The damned in a flame of fire ſhal be,</l>
                     <l>The ſaints of Love to perpetuitie.</l>
                     <l>Here flattering objects ſteal our Love away</l>
                     <l>From God, but there it never ſhal decay.</l>
                     <l>You in the morning may behold the graſs</l>
                     <l>With drops of dew al covered over, as</l>
                     <l>So many pearls but when the <hi>ſun</hi> draws near</l>
                     <l>With ſcorching beams, they ſtraightway diſappear.</l>
                     <l>Perchance wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n our affections once are ſtirr'd</l>
                     <l>Up by the quickning vertue of the VVord,</l>
                     <l>Or when we ſee the pretious bloud of Chriſt</l>
                     <l>Trickling as't were down in the Euchariſt;</l>
                     <l>Our hearts then melt with love, ſome love-drops fal</l>
                     <l>Down from the Limbecks of our eyes, but al</l>
                     <l>Again doth vaniſh in a little ſpace,</l>
                     <l>And our firſt-love declines and ſpends apace</l>
                     <l>While here on Earth we Mortals have our ſtation,</l>
                     <l>This matter is of great humiliation.</l>
                     <l>But when our God in glory we ſhal ſee,</l>
                     <l>Our Love ſhal fix'd as wel as fervent be:</l>
                     <l>It ne're ſhal taken off be any more</l>
                     <l>From him whom Saints and Angels al adore.</l>
                     <l>Such beauty in <hi>Jehovah</hi> then ſhal ſhine,</l>
                     <l>That alwayes as a Load-ſtone moſt divine,</l>
                     <l>He ſweetly ſhal attract each heart and eye,</l>
                     <l>Oh bleſſed fight! Oh rare felicity!</l>
                     <l>Between the ſaints a mutual accord</l>
                     <l>There ſhal be too, there Enmity's abhor'd;</l>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:63305:47"/>
                     <l>The Pulſe of their affection towards each other</l>
                     <l>Shal ſtrongly beat; here brother ſtrives with brother;</l>
                     <l>But in the Paradiſe above the plant</l>
                     <l>Of Love arrives at perfect growth: I grant</l>
                     <l>Our natures here are ſometime ſo defac'd,</l>
                     <l>That grace cannot ſo great a luſtre caſt.</l>
                     <l>In aiming at, that mark we here ſhoot wide,</l>
                     <l>Bad men unite, when good-men oft divide.</l>
                     <l>'Mong ſaints contentions never were more hot,</l>
                     <l>Nor Love more cold, ſaints againſt ſaints do plot;</l>
                     <l>Many there are, who Members are of Chriſt,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe muſick al in diſcords doth conſiſt,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Harp the Croſs is, who the truth pretend</l>
                     <l>To Love, but won't an ear to concord lend.</l>
                     <l>Diviſions are the powder-plot, whereby</l>
                     <l>Satan blows up the Churches unity.</l>
                     <l>Sin brought forth ſeparation, and this Daughter</l>
                     <l>Her curſed Mother too much taking after,</l>
                     <l>The Grand-child of Diviſion to our ſmart</l>
                     <l>Hath born, great thoughts &amp; ſearchings there of heart</l>
                     <l>Are for theſe things, it is no marvel I</l>
                     <l>Conceive at al to hear the Harlot cry,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pray let the Child divided be:</hi> But oh</l>
                     <l>To hear the Mother of the Child ſay ſo,</l>
                     <l>That's very ſad: No wonder 'tis to ſee</l>
                     <l>Pope, Jeſuite, and Sectary agree</l>
                     <l>To rend the bowels of their tender Mother,</l>
                     <l>But for one ſaint to perſecute another,</l>
                     <l>That's very ſtrange, 'tis ſuch a ſight as doth</l>
                     <l>Provoke to pity and amazement both.</l>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:63305:48"/>
                     <l>For VVolves to worry Lambs 'tis uſual,</l>
                     <l>For Lambs each other, that's unnatural.</l>
                     <l>It is an ordinary thing, you know,</l>
                     <l>Among the thorns to ſee Chriſts Lilly grow,</l>
                     <l>But for this Lilly to become a thorn,</l>
                     <l>And tear it ſelf, to ſee't who doth not mourn?</l>
                     <l>Well this a foil wil be the more to ſet</l>
                     <l>Off Heaven, there our Love ſhal ever get</l>
                     <l>And kept the upper hand of Enmity,</l>
                     <l>Of judgement there no difference ſhal be:</l>
                     <l>I'th journies end ſaints ſhal agree, no doubt</l>
                     <l>Though by the way they many times fal our.</l>
                     <l>When once Chriſts harp in th'ears of ſaints hath ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</l>
                     <l>The evil ſpirit ſhal be quite confounded:</l>
                     <l>VVhen to the higheſt peg of bliſs, our ſtrings</l>
                     <l>Shal once be wounded up by the King of Kings,</l>
                     <l>No diſcord in our Muſick then ſhal be,</l>
                     <l>In heaven there's a perfect harmony:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But ſtay my Muſe, forbear to proſecute</l>
                     <l>This lofty theame, leſt thou be ſtrucken mure</l>
                     <l>By th' ne're enough admired depth and height</l>
                     <l>Of heavens bliſs tranſcending al conceit.</l>
                     <l>None to the life can limne out heavens glory,</l>
                     <l>Although they ſtudy nought but Oratory.</l>
                     <l>Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> by a Biſhop of his time</l>
                     <l>Being requeſted earneſtly to climb</l>
                     <l>Up in his thoughts to the Emperial Court</l>
                     <l>Above, and of its joyes, to make report,</l>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:63305:48"/>
                     <l>VVhile he addreſt himſelf unto the task,</l>
                     <l>Attempting heavens beauty to unmask,</l>
                     <l>VVhil'ſt on the wing he ſoar'd of contemplation,</l>
                     <l>And in the depth was of his meditation,</l>
                     <l>A voice articulate, diſtinct and clear</l>
                     <l>Arrived at the portal of his ear,</l>
                     <l>Saying, what mean'ſt thou <hi>(Auſtin?)</hi> doſt thou ever</l>
                     <l>Hope to effect what thou doſt now endeavour?</l>
                     <l>Doſt thou th' expanded Ocean in thy hand</l>
                     <l>E're think to meaſure, or to graſpe the Land</l>
                     <l>VVithin thy ſhallow fiſt? Leave altogether</l>
                     <l>The ſearch of heaven till thou commeſt thither.</l>
                     <l>If that bright ſtar was by an heavenly voice</l>
                     <l>Silenc'd, and from the handling of ſo choice</l>
                     <l>A theame prohibited, How then may I</l>
                     <l>Into thoſe ſacred ſecrets dare to pry?</l>
                     <l>Let it in brief ſuffice to know that al</l>
                     <l>The Rhetorick of the Quire angelical</l>
                     <l>Is not enough to reach the top and height</l>
                     <l>Of heavens glory, pleaſure, and delight,</l>
                     <l>Nor al the bitter ſighs and helliſh groans</l>
                     <l>Of damned ſpirits and tormented ones,</l>
                     <l>Who labour under an eternal croſs,</l>
                     <l>Sufficient to bewaile ſo great a loſs.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusions">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:63305:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Practical Concluſions From the former</hi> DISCOURSE.</head>
               <div type="conclusion">
                  <lg>
                     <l>THey that expect a glorious tranſlation,</l>
                     <l>Muſt lead on Earth a gracious converſation,</l>
                     <l>Of doing wel it never muſt repent them,</l>
                     <l>A common courſe of life muſt not content them,</l>
                     <l>Their boſome-ſins they muſt eſt-ſoon diſcard,</l>
                     <l>Which do their motion heaven-ward retard,</l>
                     <l>How pure had they need be who fix their eye</l>
                     <l>Upon a place free from impurity?</l>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:63305:49"/>
                     <l>In righteouſneſs they others muſt excel,</l>
                     <l>Who hope for heaven where righteouſneſs doth dwel.</l>
                     <l>In Glories famous Univerſitie</l>
                     <l>They Graduates can never look to be,</l>
                     <l>Who are not in the ſchool of grace with ſtore</l>
                     <l>Of Piety well principled before.</l>
                     <l>Holineſs is heavens happineſs, a ſign,</l>
                     <l>Heaven was not built to be a ſty for ſwine.</l>
                     <l>No ſinful ſouls may there themſelves embark,</l>
                     <l>As unclean creatures once in <hi>Noahs</hi> ark.</l>
                     <l>The wine of angels never was nor ſhal</l>
                     <l>Be preſſed out to fill old casks withal.</l>
                     <l>Garlands of Glory they ſhal never wear,</l>
                     <l>In whom the flow'rs of Grace don't firſt appear.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:63305:50"/>
                  <head>The Second <hi>Practical Concluſion.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O Let the thoughts of heavens endleſs joy</l>
                     <l>Bear up thy heart when ſorrows would annoy;</l>
                     <l>Under temptations let thy ſoul be glad,</l>
                     <l>An intereſt in heaven and be ſad:</l>
                     <l>Although the Lead of trouble, down-ward move,</l>
                     <l>Yet let the Cork of Faith ſtill ſwim above.</l>
                     <l>This worlds afflictions, which are tranſitory,</l>
                     <l>Hold no compariſon with the weight of glory.</l>
                     <l>When melancholy did the ſcepter ſway</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s heart, he then was wont to ſay,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Remember thou art</hi> Caeſar; and thereby,</l>
                     <l>Dethroned that uſurping Enemy.</l>
                     <l>When outward croſſes on thy ſpirit lye,</l>
                     <l>Make a perſume of a perplexity,</l>
                     <l>By muſing often on thine intereſt</l>
                     <l>In God, in Chriſt, and in that place of reſt.</l>
                     <l>Where ſwallow'd up all worldly ſorrows ſhal</l>
                     <l>Where in the viſion beatifical.</l>
                     <l>St. <hi>Baſil</hi> doth of certain Martyrs write</l>
                     <l>Expoſed naked in a winters night</l>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:63305:50"/>
                     <l>To the inclemency of wind and weather</l>
                     <l>Being the next day to be burnt together:</l>
                     <l>That in this plight they were no whit diſmaid,</l>
                     <l>But comfortably to each other ſaid,</l>
                     <l>Sharp is the cold, but ſweet is Paradiſe,</l>
                     <l>This torment's nothing to that pearl of price.</l>
                     <l>The Way is thorny, and our feet may gall,</l>
                     <l>Our journies end wil make amends for al.</l>
                     <l>Let us a while endure the cold, and than</l>
                     <l>The Patriarchs boſome warm us ſhal again.</l>
                     <l>Let our feet burn, that we may when we dye</l>
                     <l>Dance with the Angels to eternity.</l>
                     <l>And ſo much joy there is in ſtore for me,</l>
                     <l>Said bleſſed <hi>Philpot,</hi> that although I be</l>
                     <l>Up in a place of doleful darkneſs pent,</l>
                     <l>Yet wretched ſinner I cannot lament,</l>
                     <l>But night and day I am as full of glee,</l>
                     <l>As if from croſſes I were wholly free.</l>
                     <l>Yea, ne're was I in al my life before</l>
                     <l>So cheer'd as now I'm landing at the ſhore:</l>
                     <l>The contemplation of eternity</l>
                     <l>Pulls out the ſting of worldly miſery.</l>
                     <l>It turns the hiſſing ſerpent of temptation</l>
                     <l>Into a bloſſoming rod of conſolation,</l>
                     <l>It makes the oyl of gladneſs ſwim and lye</l>
                     <l>Above the water of adverſity,</l>
                     <l>It out of ev'ry croſs doth take the core,</l>
                     <l>It ſucks the poyſon out of every ſore.</l>
                     <l>It draws the anguiſh out of every groan,</l>
                     <l>And cutteth each calamity of the ſtone.</l>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:63305:51"/>
                     <l>They cannot chuſe but lead a joyful life,</l>
                     <l>In whom the thoughts of heaven are moſt riſe.</l>
                     <l>That chryſtal fountain to perplexed hearts</l>
                     <l>Sweet draughts of conſolation oft imparts.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>The Third <hi>Practical Concluſion.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O Let there be within thy ſoul a dearth</l>
                     <l>Of worldly thoughts, leſt doting on the earth</l>
                     <l>Thou forfeit thoſe refined ſweets, which lie</l>
                     <l>Safe in the boſome of eternitie.</l>
                     <l>Cold comfort is in creatures to be found,</l>
                     <l>Contentment grows not in ſuch barren ground.</l>
                     <l>Heaven is the ſpring from whence a lone doth flow</l>
                     <l>Sweet ſatisfaction to the faints below.</l>
                     <l>Where others ſet their hearts, there ſet thy feet,</l>
                     <l>Such counſel for a chriſtian is moſt meet.</l>
                     <l>Spend not thy coin for that which is not bread,</l>
                     <l>But with diſdain on earths enjoyments tread.</l>
                     <l>Faſten thine eyes upon that glorious ſtate,</l>
                     <l>For which the ſaints with expectation waite.</l>
                     <l>Part not with that invaluable treaſure,</l>
                     <l>For a few drops of moment any pleaſure.</l>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:63305:51"/>
                     <l>O hazard not thy ſelf to endleſs woes,</l>
                     <l>For things that are as fading as the Roſe.</l>
                     <l>What fruit hath <hi>Dives</hi> of his rich attire,</l>
                     <l>Or dainty fare in the infernal fire?</l>
                     <l>Of her diſſolved Gems what pleaſing taſt</l>
                     <l>Hath <hi>Cleoparra</hi> now her life is paſt?</l>
                     <l>What ſweetneſs now finds <hi>Heliogabalus</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>In the <hi>Elixars</hi> of his various</l>
                     <l>And coſtly <hi>Cates?</hi> VVhat pleaſures now ariſe</l>
                     <l>From his unheard of ſenſualities?</l>
                     <l>O toy not then with beggarly delights!</l>
                     <l>Divert thine eye from earths inchanting ſights;</l>
                     <l>Reliſh no earthly joyes, nor highly priſe</l>
                     <l>The gilded pompe of worldly phantaſies:</l>
                     <l>What cares and fears gripe thoſe who thus excel?</l>
                     <l>Rich diſcontent is but a glorious hell.</l>
                     <l>Though thou to ſo journ here on earth art driven</l>
                     <l>Yet let thy Faith be breathing ſtill in heaven.</l>
                     <l>O fix thine eye upon thy future ſtation,</l>
                     <l>Let that be floating on thy meditation.</l>
                     <l>The matchleſs glory which thy preſent ſtate</l>
                     <l>Succeedeth, time ſhal never antiquate:</l>
                     <l>Let all thy ſtudies to that center tend,</l>
                     <l>The bleſſedneſs of heaven knows no end;</l>
                     <l>Be ſure to make eternity the ſphere</l>
                     <l>Of all thy thoughts even while thou liveſt here,</l>
                     <l>And let thy contemplation often be</l>
                     <l>Prying upon thy future dignity;</l>
                     <l>Be ever thinking thus, Oh when ſhall I</l>
                     <l>Take up my lodging in eternity!</l>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:63305:52"/>
                     <l>Still Rally up thy thoughts, and Muſter them</l>
                     <l>To proſecute the heavenly Diadem:</l>
                     <l>And learn with ſtudiouſneſs to methodiſe</l>
                     <l>The grand affairs in which thy ſafety lies.</l>
                     <l>O let thy ſoul unto eternity</l>
                     <l>As Eagles to the carcaſs ſwiftly flye,</l>
                     <l>And there be alwayes hovering up and down,</l>
                     <l>Till thou a fight gain of the eternal crown.</l>
                     <l>While others fill their thoughts with dirt, and go</l>
                     <l>After the muddy comforts here below,</l>
                     <l>O do not thou diſgrace and vilifie</l>
                     <l>Thy ſoul that of-ſet of divinity;</l>
                     <l>With ſuch vain contemplations don't affect</l>
                     <l>I'th' ſumptuous casket of thine intellect</l>
                     <l>To lay up pebbles; 'tis a very groſs</l>
                     <l>Sin for a ſaint to ſtudy dung and droſs,</l>
                     <l>To putrifie his thonghts with objects which</l>
                     <l>Defiling are, and oft the heart bewitch.</l>
                     <l>Our lives like Candles in the wind are here,</l>
                     <l>To which each blaſt proves an extinguiſher.</l>
                     <l>Or like to Glaſſes, that are broken by</l>
                     <l>A gentle knock, and into ſhivers flye.</l>
                     <l>There's no diſtemper but may in the wombe</l>
                     <l>Of Earth our dying carcaſes intombe.</l>
                     <l>Since then we are ſo brittle and ſo frail</l>
                     <l>Let us not ceaſe to peep within the vail,</l>
                     <l>Let's fix our thoughts upon eternal bliſs,</l>
                     <l>Which our eſtate behind the curtain is:</l>
                     <l>Our veſſels to that Haven let us ſteere</l>
                     <l>And anchor al our meditations there.</l>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:63305:52"/>
                     <l>The thoughts of Heaven put a mask before</l>
                     <l>The beauties which al carnal hearts adore.</l>
                     <l>Of ſenſual appetites they dul the edge</l>
                     <l>And caſt a ruſt upon the golden wedge.</l>
                     <l>Such contemplations do anatomiſe</l>
                     <l>The flattering world in its varieties.</l>
                     <l>And of its cheat each vein and artery</l>
                     <l>Moſt clearly and diſtinctly do deſcry.</l>
                     <l>Eternal glory ruminated on</l>
                     <l>Will ſtain the beauty of the regal throne.</l>
                     <l>'Twil raiſe the heart and the affections carry</l>
                     <l>Far above al contentments ſublunary.</l>
                     <l>This opes the eyes and make a ſaint eſpy</l>
                     <l>Much paint, impoſture, and fugacity</l>
                     <l>In the moſt rich and flouriſhing eſtate</l>
                     <l>That comes within the worldly mans conceit.</l>
                     <l>VVhen once a ſaint through Faiths proſpective glaſs</l>
                     <l>Peeps into heaven and deſcries the maſs</l>
                     <l>Of never fading wealth laid up in ſtore</l>
                     <l>For ſuch as God in purity adore,</l>
                     <l>The cream of creature comforts by and by</l>
                     <l>Grows ſtale and curdles into vanity.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Dagon</hi> ſtreight of worldly bliſs doth fall,</l>
                     <l>Before the thoughts of joy caeleſtial.</l>
                     <l>As pretty labouring <hi>Bees,</hi> although they live</l>
                     <l>I'th' midſt of wax and honey in their Hive,</l>
                     <l>Yet are their nimble wings not hindred by</l>
                     <l>That viſcous matter, that they cannot fly</l>
                     <l>Abroad, or ſwiftly paſs from flower to flower,</l>
                     <l>To gather <hi>thyme</hi> to carry to their bower.</l>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:63305:53"/>
                     <l>So thou that doſt in the abundance dwell</l>
                     <l>Of worldly Delicates as in a cell</l>
                     <l>Of ſweetneſs, ſhouldſt beware, leſt earthly things</l>
                     <l>To thine affections cleave, which are the wings</l>
                     <l>Of thine immortal ſoul, that may retard</l>
                     <l>Thy daily flight and motion heaven-ward:</l>
                     <l>That may abate thy thoughts activity</l>
                     <l>In their oft muſing on the myſtery</l>
                     <l>Of heavens bliſs, which chiefly and above</l>
                     <l>All things a ſaint delight in ſhould and love.</l>
                     <l>The Loadſtone doth its vertue loſe and can't</l>
                     <l>Iron attract plac'd neer the <hi>Adamant;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And ſhall the world thy heart draw and entice,</l>
                     <l>For all the neerneſs of the pearl of price?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hagar,</hi> no doubt, would have contented been</l>
                     <l>With her exhauſted Bottle, had ſhe ſeen</l>
                     <l>The Well that was beſide her; ſo ſhould ſaints</l>
                     <l>With little of the world, ſince God acquaints</l>
                     <l>Them with a ſpring of living water nigh,</l>
                     <l>Which ſhall refreſh them to eternity.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:63305:53"/>
                  <head>The Fourth <hi>Practical Concluſion.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THough heaven be an edifice ſo wide,</l>
                     <l>That myriads of ſouls may there reſide</l>
                     <l>Yet thither all ſhall not advanced be;</l>
                     <l>To many Chriſt will ſay, Depart from me,</l>
                     <l>I never knew you, never did approve</l>
                     <l>Of your Devotion, or pretended love;</l>
                     <l>Who Vaſſals are to ſin, cannot expect</l>
                     <l>A ſhare in bleſſedneſs with Gods Elect.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Cherubims</hi> with flaming ſwords do ſtand,</l>
                     <l>To ſtop their paſſage to the <hi>Holy Land.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Chaff may with the Wheat together lie</l>
                     <l>Here in the floor, not in the Granatie;</l>
                     <l>No ſons of <hi>Belial</hi> e're refreſhed ſhall</l>
                     <l>Be with the dews of joyes caeleſtial.</l>
                     <l>Their heads with glory never ſhall be crown'd,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe hearts were never conſecrated ground.</l>
                     <l>Such in the landskip of a ſingle glance</l>
                     <l>Shall ne're behold the ſaints inheritance.</l>
                     <l>Or if they do, 'tis to accumulate</l>
                     <l>The infelicity of their deſp'rate ſtate.</l>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:63305:54"/>
                     <l>Although the ſerpent into Paradiſe</l>
                     <l>Did winde it ſelf the VVoman to entiſe:</l>
                     <l>Yet no defiled ſoul by al its skill</l>
                     <l>Shal e're aſcend or ſcale Gods holy hill.</l>
                     <l>Great <hi>Pompeys theatre</hi> was ſtiled by</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Turtullian</hi> of al filthineſs the ſty:</l>
                     <l>But Heaven's <hi>Noneſuch,</hi> there is not the leaſt</l>
                     <l>Tincture of ſin to ſtain that place of reſt.</l>
                     <l>There no temptation ſhal the ſaints aſſaile,</l>
                     <l>No ſinful luſt ſhal lodge within the vaile.</l>
                     <l>Heaven is the ſacred and imperial court</l>
                     <l>Of Gods immediate preſence; where (in ſhort)</l>
                     <l>His purer eyes ſhal ne're offended be</l>
                     <l>VVith the leaſt riſing of deformity.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:63305:54"/>
                  <head>Marks of our Intereſt in Heaven.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THey that ſhal wear the Royal Diadem</l>
                     <l>Of glory in the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Are <hi>Scions</hi> off from Natures Olive broke</l>
                     <l>And grafted new into another ſtock.</l>
                     <l>God hath diſmantled the old man in part,</l>
                     <l>VVho full poſſeſſion once had of the heart.</l>
                     <l>Some carnal luſt falls from them ev'ry day,</l>
                     <l>That in the ſoul did formerly bear ſway.</l>
                     <l>They looſed are from the grave-cloaths of ſin,</l>
                     <l>VVhich heretofore they were involved in.</l>
                     <l>Their wonted paths they willingly forſake,</l>
                     <l>And in the wayes of God much pleaſure take.</l>
                     <l>The fignet of the word and heavenly print</l>
                     <l>Hath ſtamped on their hearts once ſatans mint.</l>
                     <l>The ſpirits gale hath blown upon them, and</l>
                     <l>Turned their courſe towards the <hi>Holy Land;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Their lives beſpangled are with holineſs,</l>
                     <l>His Vertues that hath call'd them they expreſs,</l>
                     <l>The rayes of Chriſts tranſcendent beauty ſhine</l>
                     <l>Upon them, and their hearts to him encline.</l>
                     <l>Temptations womb is in the bitths of ſin,</l>
                     <l>Leſs fruitful than it heretofore hath been.</l>
                     <l>The weeds of luſt decay in them apace,</l>
                     <l>And in their room ſprings up the Herb of Grace.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:63305:55"/>
                  <head>The Second Mark</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THeir ſouls are carried out with violence,</l>
                     <l>Heaven to attain they pine at no expence.</l>
                     <l>As Gods redeemed <hi>Iſrael</hi> by his aid</l>
                     <l>The Land of Promiſe ſtoutly did invade:</l>
                     <l>So his Elect and choſen Generation</l>
                     <l>Lay ſiege unto the heavenly habitation.</l>
                     <l>There's no arriving at eternal life,</l>
                     <l>They know full well, without this holy ſtrife.</l>
                     <l>To heaven with all celerity they hie,</l>
                     <l>As flocks of Doves unto their windows flie,</l>
                     <l>They march on ſpeedily without delay,</l>
                     <l>Although there be a Lion in the way.</l>
                     <l>The wings of Faith bear them above thoſe fears,</l>
                     <l>Which carnal hearts do penetrate like ſpears.</l>
                     <l>They break through all obſtructions that they may</l>
                     <l>Poſſeſs themſelves of their intended prey.</l>
                     <l>The batt'ries of their prai'rs'gainſt heaven they plant</l>
                     <l>And ſtorm't, till God to them an entrance grant:</l>
                     <l>They ask in Faith and will not be denied,</l>
                     <l>Heaven they muſt have, what e're they want beſide.</l>
                     <l>At this they aim, to this each ſaint aſpires,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> here's the center of their choice deſires.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:63305:55"/>
                  <head>The Third Mark.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THey by the new and living way do go</l>
                     <l>The vaile of Chriſts humanity; they know,</l>
                     <l>That there is no ſalvation to be had</l>
                     <l>In any other: if they be not clad</l>
                     <l>VVith his unſpotted robes of righteouſneſs,</l>
                     <l>They can't be ſav'd in any other dreſs.</l>
                     <l>There's no name under heaven that can eaſe us</l>
                     <l>Of ſins enthralment, but the name of <hi>Jeſus.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Saints by his merits only do attain</l>
                     <l>Eternal life, which is the greateſt gain.</l>
                     <l>Good works to heavens kingdom are the way,</l>
                     <l>The cauſe of reigning that we dare not ſay.</l>
                     <l>Chriſt is the Door, and there's no entring in</l>
                     <l>But by his bloud, which clonſeth from all ſin:</l>
                     <l>He is the curtain, the refreſhing ſcreen,</l>
                     <l>Us and Gods ſcorching ire that ſtands between</l>
                     <l>The deluge of his wrath no man can ſhun,</l>
                     <l>Unleſs with ſpeed into this ark he run:</l>
                     <l>They loſe themſelves for ever, who aſſay</l>
                     <l>To go to heaven any other way.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:63305:56"/>
                  <head>The Fourth Mark.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THeir ſouls oft ſoar above the ſpangled sky,</l>
                     <l>And unto Heaven in contemplation fly;</l>
                     <l>Mount <hi>Tabor</hi> they do frequently aſcend,</l>
                     <l>To eye the glory that may there be kenn'd:</l>
                     <l>They heaven alwayes have within their eye,</l>
                     <l>VVhich makes them earthly trifles to defie.</l>
                     <l>Their hearts are only fix'd on things above,</l>
                     <l>Theſe are the chiefeſt objects of their love.</l>
                     <l>The bleſſed God their thoughts ſtill dwel upon,</l>
                     <l>An eartely ſaint's a contradiction.</l>
                     <l>Though they to ſo journ here below are driven,</l>
                     <l>Yet is their converſation ſtill in heaven:</l>
                     <l>There is their treaſure, there their chief eſtate,</l>
                     <l>From which no wile their hearts can ſeparate.</l>
                     <l>How to be great on earth is not their plot,</l>
                     <l>They uſe the world as though they us'd it not.</l>
                     <l>The pleaſures of this life they little heed,</l>
                     <l>Their thoughts upon the faireſt objects feed.</l>
                     <l>They'r alwayes preſſing forward tow'rds the <hi>mark,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And long to taſte the <hi>Manna</hi> in heav'ns ark.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="conclusion">
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:63305:56"/>
                  <head>The Fifth <hi>Practical Concluſion.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O Long to be inſtalled in the throne</l>
                     <l>Of endleſs glory, let thy ſpirit groan</l>
                     <l>After a full and plenary poſſeſſion</l>
                     <l>Of bleſſedneſs tranſcending all expreſſion;</l>
                     <l>Pant after that unparallell'd eſtate,</l>
                     <l>One mite whereof ſurpaſſeth all conceit.</l>
                     <l>Be like the Bird of Paradiſe, which (they ſay)</l>
                     <l>Being intangled in the ſnare, ſtraightway</l>
                     <l>Begins to ſtrive, and never giveth o're</l>
                     <l>Till ſhe enjoy her freedom as before.</l>
                     <l>Sing <hi>Simeons</hi> ſwan-like ſong at his deceaſe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lord, let thy ſervant now depart in peace.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Welcome the meſſenger of death, which brings</l>
                     <l>Moſt joyful tydings from the King of Kings;</l>
                     <l>Which tells the ſaints of an approaching crown</l>
                     <l>Of matchleſs glory, honour, and renown.</l>
                     <l>Death is the chariot, which without delay</l>
                     <l>Saints to their Fathers houſe ſoon bears away.</l>
                     <l>Death lodgeth ſouls, i'th' twinckling of an eye,</l>
                     <l>In the ſweet boſome of felicity:</l>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:63305:57"/>
                     <l>Death is to humble penitents no leſs</l>
                     <l>Then a ſhort entrance into happineſs:</l>
                     <l>Their naſty loathſome rags death frees them from,</l>
                     <l>And gives them change of raiment in their room.</l>
                     <l>Death is the ſaints aſcenſion day to bliſs,</l>
                     <l>Their marriage day with Jeſus Chriſt it is.</l>
                     <l>Death is the Charter of their liberty,</l>
                     <l>The period of their pain and miſery:</l>
                     <l>Death gives them an immunity from ſin,</l>
                     <l>And frees them from the fears they once were in:</l>
                     <l>Death is the bane of woe, the grave of vice,</l>
                     <l>The portal opening into Paradiſe.</l>
                     <l>Where grace, that in the bud was here below,</l>
                     <l>Into the flow'r of glory ſtraight ſhal blow,</l>
                     <l>Where ſaints immortal ſouls made more divine</l>
                     <l>Shal with the Di'monds of perfection ſhine.</l>
                     <l>Where they to their unſpeakable delight</l>
                     <l>Of God himſelf ſhal have a perfect ſight;</l>
                     <l>VVhere in their wills there ſhal a likeneſs be</l>
                     <l>To God in holineſs and purity.</l>
                     <l>VVhere having ſhot the gulph of Death they ſhal</l>
                     <l>VVear on their heads a crown imperial.</l>
                     <l>VVhere the rich caskets of their ſouls ſhal be</l>
                     <l>O'relaid with glories beſt embroiderie.</l>
                     <l>VVhere in the river they of pleaſures ſhal</l>
                     <l>Be bath'd, whoſe ſweetneſs is perpetual.</l>
                     <l>VVhere no contaminating tincture e're</l>
                     <l>Shall their unſpotted purity beſmear.</l>
                     <l>VVhere God himſelf unto the ſaints ſhall be</l>
                     <l>A ſpring of life to perpetuitie.</l>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:63305:57"/>
                     <l>Where they ſhal in the fragrant boſome li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of their beloved to eternitie;</l>
                     <l>Where ſaints by vertue of their Saviours merit</l>
                     <l>Shal alwayes have freſh in-comes of the ſpirit.</l>
                     <l>VVhere the enammel of their glory ſhal</l>
                     <l>Never wear off, nor ſoiled be at all.</l>
                     <l>VVhere they ſhal have a rich redundancy</l>
                     <l>Of peace, joy, comfort and ſerenity.</l>
                     <l>Where they their ſafety ſhal behold from all</l>
                     <l>Inſulting foes, and their eternal thrall.</l>
                     <l>VVhere they a glorious kingdom ſhal receive,</l>
                     <l>Of which no power on earth can them bereave.</l>
                     <l>VVhere they ſhal be partakers of that joy,</l>
                     <l>VVhich will them ſatisfie, but never cloy.</l>
                     <l>VVhere <hi>Baca</hi> into <hi>Beracha</hi> ſhal be</l>
                     <l>Converted, mourning into melody.</l>
                     <l>VVhere briniſh tears ſhal never dim their eyes,</l>
                     <l>Nor ſhal their ears be frighted more with cryes.</l>
                     <l>Where ſorrows ne're ſhal damp their hearrs again,</l>
                     <l>Nor ſhal their ſenſes be diſturb'd with pain.</l>
                     <l>VVhere they no more ſhal perſecuted be</l>
                     <l>By Satans imps for their integrity.</l>
                     <l>VVhere ſaints with ſparkling Gems of glory ſhal</l>
                     <l>Be deck'd, and not be envi'd for't at all.</l>
                     <l>VVhere length of years without the leaſt decay</l>
                     <l>Of ſtrength they ſhal enjoy; yea, where for ay</l>
                     <l>They ſhal be bleſſed with the love of many,</l>
                     <l>And need not fear the jealoufie of any:</l>
                     <l>VVhere for their labour a <hi>Quietus eſt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Each ſaint ſhal have, and ever be at reſt.</l>
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:63305:58"/>
                     <l>Where life and immortality they ſhall</l>
                     <l>Have for their death in Chriſt, and Chriſt for all.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The Concluſion of the whole.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe Glory that within the curtain lies</l>
                  <l>Can't meaſur'd be by our capacities.</l>
                  <l>There's more within the vaile than by the beſt</l>
                  <l>And moſt ſublimed ſaint can be expreſt;</l>
                  <l>Grace may believe't, but Reaſon cannot ſound</l>
                  <l>The bottom of't, though never ſo profound.</l>
                  <l>In fathoming this rich inheritance,</l>
                  <l>What's all acuteneſs but meer ignorance?</l>
                  <l>He cannot reach this glory that's indu'de</l>
                  <l>VVith knowledge in the largeſt latitude.</l>
                  <l>If Natures ſecretary did not know</l>
                  <l>The cauſe why <hi>Euripus</hi> did ebbe and flow,</l>
                  <l>O how then would his Reaſon puzz'led be</l>
                  <l>To ſound the Ocean of Eternity?</l>
                  <l>VVhat the inſpired Pen-man doth relate</l>
                  <l>Of natural men and unregenerate,</l>
                  <l>Reſpectively to ſpir'tuals, that they are</l>
                  <l>Not able them to comprehend or bear:</l>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:63305:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>The ſame more truly may aſſerted be,</l>
                  <l>In reference unto Eternity.</l>
                  <l>'Tis with the proſpect of eternity</l>
                  <l>As to the Ocean it is with the eye:</l>
                  <l>It may its ſurface, not its bottom ſee.</l>
                  <l>And ſo ſome dark and glimmering knowledge we</l>
                  <l>May have of heaven, but no mortal eye</l>
                  <l>Into its in ſide able is to pry.</l>
                  <l>The blind-man half reſtored to his ſight</l>
                  <l>Said, <hi>Lo, I ſee by this imperfect light</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Men walk as trees:</hi> So may a pur-blind eye</l>
                  <l>Glance at the riches of Eternity.</l>
                  <l>Some few weak parcels of the knowledge we</l>
                  <l>May of it gain, but not its Centre ſee.</l>
                  <l>He that was carri'd up above the sky,</l>
                  <l>To ſee a Landskip of Felicity,</l>
                  <l>To take a view of thoſe tranſcendencies</l>
                  <l>Heaven was enrich'd withal, what there his eyes</l>
                  <l>Had ſeen to their ineffable content,</l>
                  <l>At his return with what aſtoniſhment</l>
                  <l>Doth he relate it! Yea, he doth confeſs,</l>
                  <l>Words were too weak his Viſion to expreſs:</l>
                  <l>The raviſhing and beatifical</l>
                  <l>Sights, which his eyes had bleſſed been withal,</l>
                  <l>VVere not to be pourtrai'd in all their glory</l>
                  <l>By th' Pencil of the rareſt Oratory.</l>
                  <l>The riches that attend Eternity</l>
                  <l>Tranſcend the reach of any mortal eye:</l>
                  <l>They are a ſphear above the apprehenſions</l>
                  <l>Of humane underſtandings or inventions.</l>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:63305:59"/>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> though height'ned much with induſtry</l>
                  <l>And Grace, their worth and value can't deſcry.</l>
                  <l>Eternal glory to our weaker eyes</l>
                  <l>Is an eſtate vail'd o're with myſteries,</l>
                  <l>Much like to pictures, whoſe rare artifice</l>
                  <l>By Curtains from our eyes concealed is.</l>
                  <l>The lanthorn of our ſhallow intellect</l>
                  <l>Us to the knowledge of it can't direct.</l>
                  <l>VVhile grace is of ſo low a ſtature, we</l>
                  <l>Can't look that knowledge ſhould giganticke be.</l>
                  <l>None can of Glory have a perfect ſight,</l>
                  <l>Till they from earth to heaven take their flight:</l>
                  <l>The winter of our life muſt firſt be paſt,</l>
                  <l>E're we the ſummer fruits of glory taſte;</l>
                  <l>VVhen ſaints out of the cage of earth ſhall flye</l>
                  <l>Into the Region of eternity,</l>
                  <l>Their pondrous weights of glory they ſhall find</l>
                  <l>To <hi>nonplus</hi> all conceptions of the mind.</l>
                  <l>Till that time come they muſt contented be</l>
                  <l>VVith the firſt fruits of that felicitie.</l>
                  <l>VVith thoſe ſweet crums their craving ſtomacks they</l>
                  <l>Muſt pacifie till their aſcenſion day.</l>
                  <l>The fuller knowledge of our future ſtate</l>
                  <l>Concealed is, our Faith to animate.</l>
                  <l>VVho dig in Mines where ſtore of Gold doth lye,</l>
                  <l>Their hopes of wealth do whet their induſtry.</l>
                  <l>Many Reſerves there are in heaven which</l>
                  <l>Magnetick are to draw out all the rich</l>
                  <l>And orient Graces of the ſaints, and theſe</l>
                  <l>VVarm their endeavours, that are apt to freeze.</l>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:63305:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>VVhat in the dark remains doth grace excit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>And ſcrue it up unto a greater height:</l>
                  <l>Such a deſire of knowledge natural</l>
                  <l>VVas that ingenious Romane edg'd withal,</l>
                  <l>That while the cauſe he of <hi>Veſuvius</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>His flaming Vomits with a vigorous</l>
                  <l>Enquiry ſought to know, he in the wombe</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe ejections did himſelf entombe.</l>
                  <l>And how doth this lend Grace a wing to fly,</l>
                  <l>And with more vigorous conqueſt it ſupply!</l>
                  <l>That he, whoſe eye of Faith moſt piercing is,</l>
                  <l>Can't ſee the end of his eternal bliſs,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſum up what the int'reſt of his Glory</l>
                  <l>Amounts to by the light of ſacred ſtory.</l>
                  <l>This portion, which our intellects can't ſee</l>
                  <l>To tell out while they vail'd and clouded be,</l>
                  <l>Is a moſt rich and rare encouragement,</l>
                  <l>VVhereby our graces with a ſtronger bent</l>
                  <l>Are carri'd heaven-ward; this Faith enflames,</l>
                  <l>And makes our hope riſe higher in its aims.</l>
                  <l>This plumes a ſaint, and makes him higher flie</l>
                  <l>In contemplation of eternitie.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:63305:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Faith's Triumph.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ST and not my ſoul upon a ſinners leggs,</l>
                  <l>But with all ſpeed relinquiſh thine own dreggs,</l>
                  <l>Into the arms of thy dear Saviour flie,</l>
                  <l>There only mayſt thou find ſecuritie:</l>
                  <l>Endeavour to beleeve what thou art never</l>
                  <l>Able to purchaſe by thine own endeavour:</l>
                  <l>Thy debt acknowledge, and then by and by</l>
                  <l>Thy Jeſus will the payment juſtifie,</l>
                  <l>Confide not in thy ſelf or what thou haſt,</l>
                  <l>Leſt by thy ſelf thou be deceiv'd at laſt:</l>
                  <l>Wouldſt thou the precious Grace of Faith acquire?</l>
                  <l>Renounce thy ſelf, caſt off thine own attire.</l>
                  <l>Wouldſt thou in purity preſerve thy Faith?</l>
                  <l>Condemne thy ſelf, heed not what Reaſon ſaith:</l>
                  <l>Do miſty clouds obſcure and dimme thy ſight?</l>
                  <l>Faith will diſpel them by its radiant light.</l>
                  <l>Is Heaven gate faſt up againſt thee blockt?</l>
                  <l>The Key of Faith will open and unlock't:</l>
                  <l>Is there in Heavens high-way a roaring <hi>Lion?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Faith will o're com't and lead thee unto <hi>Sion.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Doth fear ſurprize thee? Faith will courage bring:</l>
                  <l>Doth Death affright thee? Faith pulls out the ſting.</l>
                  <l>Is't hard and difficult to gain the crown?</l>
                  <l>Faith bear'ſt away with honour and renown.</l>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:63305:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>Be faithful to the death and thou ſhalt ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>An heavenly garland, though an earthly g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ve.</l>
                  <l>It ſhall not be to thee (the Scripture ſaith)</l>
                  <l>According to thy works but to thy faith:</l>
                  <l>If before Faith good works can't work ſalvation,</l>
                  <l>After Repentance bad ones can't damnation.</l>
                  <l>As he that crowns thy good works doth thereby</l>
                  <l>Crown his own gifts, ſo doth he magnifie</l>
                  <l>His own free Grace, that pardoneth thine evil</l>
                  <l>Works, which enſlaved thee unto the Devil;</l>
                  <l>Caſt anchor here my ſoul, let nothing e're</l>
                  <l>Remove thee, in thy Faith ſtill perſevere.</l>
                  <l>And when the waves of thy corruptions beat</l>
                  <l>Into thy leaking veſſel, and do threat</l>
                  <l>Thine utter ruine and eternal bane,</l>
                  <l>By true Repentance pumpe them out again.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
